Chapter 4: Revision

Chapter 4 - Revision

The days until Hermione could leave for Hogwarts seemed to drag at first. She was extremely eager to study her actual school books, but Professor McGonagall had been quite explicit that practising spellcasting or potion making at home was 'quite out of the question'. Since that was the obvious next step after memorizing them, she knew that not being able to practice would drive her round the bend, so she decided to save them until the last possible minute.

Instead, she tore her way (metaphorically!) through the other books she'd picked up. After all, there was a lot of background information most of the other students would already know just by virtue of having grown up in wizarding homes. She figured it might well make learning actual magic easier to have that down first.

She'd read Modern Magical History, Great Wizarding Events of the Twentieth Century, The Rise and Fall of the Dark Arts, and of course Hogwarts, A History. Then she'd read them again. She tried a third time, but she'd basically memorized them by that point.

And that was the first week.

After a couple of days of making notes on what she'd read and trying to draw some new conclusions, she convinced her mother to take her back to Diagon Alley for more books to fill in obvious gaps in her knowledge. She'd also suggested that there were a few things she'd read about that her mother really ought to buy right away and keep around the house - potions and pre-enchanted items that muggles could still use, even if they couldn't make them, for emergency first-aid and such. She was a little uncertain as to what interactions there might be - if say, heaven-forbid, her parents had a need for a blood-replenishing potion, it might end up confusing doctors after going to the hospital, and if they couldn't tell them what they'd taken… Hermione decided until she could confirm with someone knowledgeable about both magic and muggle medicine - if such a person existed - that such things wouldn't do more harm than good, she'd only recommend ostensibly 'naturopathic' remedies, like Essence of Dittany and the like.

Hermione ended up buying An Appraisal of Magical Education in Europe, Hogwarts Houses: Heaven-Sent or Hardly Worth It?, Dragon Species of Great Britain and Ireland, a copy of the Legislative Guide to the Proper Use of Magic, Practical Household Magic and the Standard Book of Spells, Grade 2. She'd selected the latter two to make sure she would have enough materials to work beyond the standard curriculum if she needed to, but firmly placed them with the other school books she was holding off on reading. The rest she read, and re-read, and took notes on.

And that was the second and third week.

Now there were only two weeks left, and though Hermione did understand on some level how smart she was, and took innocent joy in sharing things she'd learned with other people, she'd somehow never developed overconfidence when it came to studying. So with 'so little time' remaining, she was starting to get a bit nervous and finally dove into the actual books her Hogwarts classes had assigned, reading each of them at least three times, to be sure she'd fully memorized every word.

And that was the fourth week.

Having memorized her copy of Magical Theory, Hermione was now quite confident she could control when she tried to do magic and when she didn't. More specifically, that it would be safe to practice spell incantations and wand motions with no actual intent to cast a spell without either running afoul of the Decree for the Reasonable Restriction of Underage Sorcery, or producing Accidental Magic. But she didn't want to risk associating a mental habit of not intending to cast a spell along with the full motions and wording, so she decided to practice each element separately instead.

In that vein, she broke down the wand movements from all the spells in the Standard books (Grade 1 and 2) as well as Practical Household Magic, and found that there were a great many common elements - swishes, flicks, circles (widdershins and deosil) and so on - that, if mastered, would make it much easier to quickly learn any spell, so she drew up a practice schedule. She also continued on with her juggling and sleight-of-hand exercises, and made a point of practicing the wand motions with either hand.

The incantations were another matter. The vast majority of them seemed to be based on Classical Latin, though the pronunciation often differed from the accepted norms. Given how long magical history seemed to stretch back, Hermione surmised that the magical pronunciation might actually be closer to the genuine original usage, since for muggles Latin was a 'dead language' and the accepted pronunciations had been reconstructed largely through theory, whereas wizards had apparently been using them continuously for at least twenty-five hundred years. Either that, or there was some magical significance to changes in normal pronunciation, but if that was the case, it wasn't discussed in Waffling's introductory text. Hermione made a note to look into it when she had a chance, but for the moment, she sensibly practiced the incantations according to her Hogwarts books and not the ones from her local library.

Finally, the date marked on the ticket Professor McGonagall had given her came. Hermione made sure her parents got her to Kings Cross Station by 8 AM, a good three hours before the Hogwarts Express was scheduled to depart. Partially this was just due to her naturally responsible nature, but part of it was due to a loophole (though Hermione refused to use that term, even in her head, and firmly considered it an 'interesting fact') she had discovered in the Decree for the Reasonable Restriction of Underage Sorcery. Namely that the Hogwarts Express, being wholly owned and operated by the school, was legally considered part of Hogwarts itself, and thus the Decree did not apply to spells cast while on the train. It didn't even have to be in motion. And since the train (and platform nine and three-quarters) was used solely for the purpose of transporting Hogwarts students, it arrived at the station quite early in the morning and simply sat there until the posted departure time. Taken together, that meant an enterprising student might theoretically get in nearly twelve hours (counting travel time) of spellcasting practice, at least ninety minutes of which were likely to be largely uninterrupted.

After Professor McGonagall's thorough explanation, Hermione had accepted that the law was primarily meant to avoid students endangering themselves or others while trained professionals were not conveniently nearby to undo the results of any mishaps. So in that sense, since school faculty usually arrived at Hogwarts well before classes began and thus were typically not present on the Express, casting spells on the train might be considered violating the spirit of the Decree, if not the letter. Hermione wrestled with this ethical dilemma for some time, but eventually decided that since she intended to be very responsible and only practice the simplest and most harmless spells, and even then, there would be upper-year Prefects on the train who could be summoned in an emergency, that it would be irresponsible of her not to take advantage of the very limited window of opportunity she'd found to practice before arriving at the school, and would thus try not to feel too bad about it.

After arriving at King's Cross Station, her parents helped her get her trunks (she'd ended up needing two, to fit all the extra books - magical and muggle - she'd wanted to bring) onto a cart and accompanied her to to the vicinity of platform 10.

"Well," said Hermione's father. "I guess this is where we get off." Her mother was smiling but clearly trying to hold back tears. Hermione had never really been away from home for any length of time, and now she was going to leave for nearly four months, until Christmas break. Hermione suddenly regretted asking to be dropped off early so she could get extra practice. The train ride itself was over eight hours long, she could've spent the extra three hours having breakfast with her parents, watching mum and dad trade sections of the Times, double-checking to make sure she hadn't left any books she'd regret not having.

"You could come onto the platform with me, I'm sure it would be all right," she said.

"No, no...I'll just make a scene," insisted her mother. "I don't want to give the...other parents a worse impression of us than…" she trailed off without finishing the thought. The three stood in awkward silence for a moment. They all knew - Hermione from her extensive reading, the Grangers from various anecdotes in So, Your Daughter's a Witch - that the typical magical attitude towards muggles could be described as, at best, 'condescendingly tolerant'. The young girl suddenly hugged her parents fiercely.

"I love you so much...I miss you already! I'll try to make you proud," she said, her face half-buried between their shoulders as they crouched down to hug her properly.

"Of course you will, sweetheart. You're destined for great things," whispered her father, huskily, his voice slightly muffled by her stubbornly bushy hair. Hermione felt a twinge of alarm, and deja vu. The word 'destiny' floated through her mind, but couldn't find anything to attach to and faded away, taking the alarm with it. They held each other for as long as they could ignore the disruption they were causing in traffic between the platforms, and even a few moments beyond, but the Granger responsibility streak ran deep, and they broke apart.

"I snuck extra brushes and paste into your trunk, enough for an entire term...for all we know they're still using swine bristles and ground oyster shells," said Mr. Granger, trying to lighten the mood.

"I read once of an old toothpaste recipe that included 'dragon's blood'," Mrs. Granger added, smiling tremulously. Hermione laughed nervously with both of them, and did not mention that her book on dragons had in fact noted the creatures' blood had many uses, including cleaning properties, and was mostly non-toxic, so the anecdote was more plausible than it sounded. She took a deep breath.

"Okay. I'm ready. Help me get it going?" Hermione asked. The cart was tricky to start moving, so loaded down as it was. Her parents took hold of the cart's handle on either side of their daughter and pushed until she could guide it alone. Hermione made sure it was aimed properly at the barrier between platforms nine and ten, then turned to wave over her shoulder at them as she pushed until there was a sudden shimmer, then her parents were gone, and she was looking back at wrought-iron archway labeled 'Platform 9 ¾'.

o-o-o

Hermione sunk back into one of the seats of her compartment, relieved. She'd tested a few of the simple spells from Practical Household Magic, and they'd all worked perfectly on her first try (the upholstery in the compartment was now quite fresh, the windows were spotless and the compartment door opened and closed smoothly with nary a sound). In fact, they were easy. Which she supposed was the point...if household spells were difficult, people would just do those things the normal way, wouldn't they?

As it happened, she'd ended up casting her first spell almost immediately after arriving. The platform was quite deserted - if there were to be any porters for the train, they hadn't arrived yet, and Hermione was left to puzzle out how to get her two heavy trunks up the stairs into a car on her own. A quick mental review of the contents of Practical Household Magic suggested a Floating Charm, which was recommended for use when you had weighty things to carry but didn't want to pay the fixed attention to them a Levitation Charm would require. She'd stepped onto the stairs into the car first - so she was technically on the train, as her narrow interpretation of the law required - ran through the incantation and gesture a few times in her mind, and only then went ahead and tried it on her trunks. Sure enough, their weight had been essentially removed, so she could just tug them behind her as if they were half-filled helium balloons, albeit ones that still retained the inertia of fully-loaded trunks.

And the excitement from a properly cast spell was, well...almost addictive. Her memory of producing sparks from her wand - after trying several that did nothing - that first time in Ollivanders felt curiously matter-of-fact, almost dull, as if she'd done it (or seen it done) innumerable times. But this...this was something else, entirely. Sometimes, when she'd been reading a particularly advanced book or working out some tricky bit of math and suddenly understood a concept or realized what the solution was, there was this wonderful feeling, mostly in her head (her mother had said it was probably 'endorphins'). But casting spells, it was like that, only in her head, and her arm, and sometimes her whole body.

Concerned that if she let herself become distracted by continuing to test spells, she'd lose track of time, Hermione elected to change into her school robes now to get it out of the way. She didn't have a particular aversion to changing in front of other girls if she ended up sharing the compartment, but there was nothing to say the compartments would be segregated by gender, so there might well be boys, too. While Hogwarts was a boarding school, so she assumed the other students would be more mature than her previous classmates had been, she hadn't checked the size of the train bathrooms yet, so she decided better to be safe than sorry. Once she'd finished and packed away her muggle clothing, she went back to trying out spells.

Eventually, Hermione began to notice a lot more people though the outside and inside windows. Her stomach fluttered a bit as she imagined meeting other students. She hoped she'd read enough to make a good impression. Maybe things here would be different, since witches and wizards were so rare, everyone would have something in common and make friends naturally and there wouldn't be any issues…

The door to the compartment slid open (still noiselessly) and a girl entered. She was Hermione's age, and also already wearing her Hogwarts robes, though she was quite pretty, with dazzling red hair.

"Are any of these seats taken?" she asked.

"Not yet, feel free," responded Hermione cheerfully. "I'm Hermione Granger," she added.

"Mary Sue Bottomwater, nice to meet you," the girl said, with almost saccharine sweetness. Hermione's reading had prepared her for the sometimes bizarre wizard surnames, but this seemed like a particularly silly example, and she had to make a deliberate effort not to react to it. "Are you a first-year too?" the girl asked.

"Oh, yes. I'm a bit nervous, to be honest, but excited. You?" Mary Sue shrugged at Hermione's question.

"I wouldn't say nervous, but I'm very excited, I can't wait. Usually there's an exam first thing. I suppose you've already finished memorizing all your school books too?" she asked casually. Hermione's smile faltered. There would be an exam as soon as they got there? She hadn't read anything about that…

"I have, but I didn't know there'd be an exam so soon...I should probably do some revision on the way just to be sure," she answered, uncertainly. Mary Sue's eyes widened, and her smile broadened in what Hermione utterly failed to interpret as a 'devilish' way.

"Oh, good!" exclaimed the girl. "We can quiz each other! Me first. What was the trigger for the 1486 Goblin Rebellion?"

"Oh, um...it's believed to be a reaction to Yardley Platt, the notorious Dark Wizard who made a hobby of horrifically murdering goblins. Let's see, what's the second ingredient in a Forgetfulness Potion?" Mary Sue seemed surprised Hermione had answered so quickly, but came back quickly herself.

"Two Valerian sprigs," she answered, correctly. "What syllables are stressed in the Levitation Charm?"

"'Gar' and 'o'," responded Hermione. "What's the Second Principle of Transfiguration?"

"The more similarities two things share to begin with, the less concentration it takes to change one to the other. How can you tell a Devil's Snare from a Flitterbloom?"

The girls went back and forth in this fashion for several minutes, Hermione getting more and more enthusiastic while Mary Sue seemed to become increasingly frustrated and suspicious. Finally, the redhead threw her hands up in exasperation and her voice dropped an octave and lost all pretense at cheerfulness.

"Alright, let's come clean. Obviously you're not a first year - if Charlie told you about my brilliant prank idea even though he swore he wouldn't, I am going to give him a hex he won't soon forget! Unless you are Charlie?" The girl narrowed her eyes suspiciously.

"What?" asked Hermione, quite confused by the sudden turn the conversation had taken.

"Oh, come off it. Tell me who you really are, or I'll see for myself," Mary Sue said warningly.

"I already told you, my name's Hermione Granger. What are you talking about? What prank?"

"Have it your way, then," the other girl said grimly, drawing her wand - yellowish, with dark brown rings up the shaft. She pointed it at Hermione, made a complicated half-twist with a figure-eight loop and said, "Homorphus!". Hermione gaped at her and drew her own wand, though she couldn't bring a defensive spell to mind before Mary Sue finished her own. But nothing seemed to happen, other than Mary Sue's expression becoming as confused as Hermione's.

"I know it's technically legal to cast spells on the Hogwarts Express, but I'm fairly certain students casting spells at each other is at the very least frowned upon if not expressly forbidden," said Hermione sternly. "Besides, I don't even know what that spell was supposed to do, and I've read all the way through Grade 2...who are you, then?"

"So...you are a first year? And you've actually memorized all your school books?" the girl asked, ignoring Hermione's question for the moment.

"Yes, of course!" said Hermione, a bit testily. "Is that...not something Hogwarts students normally do?" she asked, somewhat hesitantly. She'd been so relieved when the girl had first mentioned that… Mary Sue meanwhile sat heavily onto one of the compartments' seats and laughed, shaking her head ruefully.

"Serves me right, I guess," she said, seemingly to herself. "Charlie will wet himself when he hears, though I suppose he's actually in Romania by now." She waved her wand over her black Hogwarts robes, which shimmered and became a rather larger set of open brown leather robes, over another blousy set in shades of black and grey. The girl herself shook slightly and grew to fill out the clothes - she looked several years older now - while her face became somewhat less pretty and her hair turned, for some reason, purple. She tucked her wand into a sleeve.

"Name's actually Tonks," she said to Hermione. "Graduated last year, and thought I'd have a spot of fun since I happened to have a free day, and get in some infiltration practice. Some first-years show up thinking they already know everything and it's good to deflate them a bit, whereas others can use a good scare to break the tension, and maybe a few kindly tips for any who are already scared to death and need a little lift. When you claimed you'd memorized your books, I thought you were just copying me and were the first sort, but I guess you actually do know everything." She grinned. Hermione just stared at her for a moment. If this was the sort of thing Hogwarts graduates thought was a good idea, her hopes about the maturity level of boarding school students seemed rather less likely to be fulfilled. She put her own wand away, with mild reluctance.

"I don't know everything...I've only had five weeks or so to read," she said, a bit defensively. "But you're saying...to scare first-years, you Transfigured yourself, and were pretending to have memorized all your books." Hermione wasn't sure how to feel about that. It seemed a bit far to go for a prank, and besides that, it didn't sound particularly complimentary towards Hermione herself.

"I have a trick for that, actually. And hey," said Tonks, noticing the downturn in Hermione's mood, "don't sweat it. It's nothing to be ashamed of...imagine all the free time you'll have, not needing to study!"

"I suppose…" said Hermione, though she found it difficult to imagine not studying.

"Well, you could always help other people study. That's actually a good tip for someone like you, come to think of it. You know about House points and all that?" Hermione nodded. "Well, the better Professors will give you just as many - if not more - points for helping students in other houses as they do for actually answering questions in class yourself. Just a thought," she finished, offhandedly.

"Were you in Hufflepuff?" asked Hermione.

"Yep. That obvious?"

"Well, your suggestion did seem very Hufflepuff, from what I've read. Though I've also read that the supposed House virtues aren't quite so fundamental as they're made out to be. I've been very curious what House I'll be Sorted into, you see." Tonks laughed again.

"I'm not the most Puffy of 'Puffs, I'll admit. I can't help looking for ways to get around rules, it's a sickness. But you're right, after graduation the Houses don't mean all that much, and even in school they're not that definitive. The virtues are definitely there, though, whether because people were Sorted because they already had 'em or because they know the reputation and think they need to live up to them, like-" she adopted a gruff masculine tone, and her chin briefly grew to heroic proportions, "'Well, I'm in Gryffindor, so I'd better fling myself into danger like a complete prat! Charge!'" Hermione laughed, despite herself.

"They're not all like that...some of 'em are even more devoted pranksters than I am, and it does take true bravery to try to get away with anything while McGonagall is hovering over your House... But there can be cleverness in Hufflepuff, and helpfulness in Gryffindor, new Ravenclaws are constantly hatching devious plans to get into the Restricted Section, and hell, I've even seen bravery from Slytherins on occasion." She paused in thought for a moment.

"I think what it comes down to is, you ought to be in a house that'll help you make the most out of Hogwarts. Either surround you with people you can use as good examples for something you want to bring out in yourself, or at least who you'll be able to just get along with for seven years." Hermione nodded. From that perspective, Slytherin didn't sound much better, but Gryffindor seemed a little less attractive than it had - she had a dim view of pranking from her years in school thus far, however Tonks might rationalize it.

"But...it's up to the Sorting Hat, right?" she asked.

"Well, little secret...the Hat can be negotiated with. You can't fool it, as far as I know, but you can maybe convince it, if you have good reasons. My mum had enough trouble after marrying my dad...I didn't want to get in the middle of any pointless rivalries, so I asked the Hat to keep me out of Slytherin or Gryffindor, and Merlin knows I only study in extreme emergencies - like trying to meet the Auror qualifications - so Ravenclaw was out. I made the best of it...Ravens may get better marks, but a 'Puff will never refuse to help if you ask, and I'll take a study group of four patient 'Puffs over one reluctant Raven any day. Not that you couldn't be a helpful Raven if you wanted. In the end, you decide who you want to be, not which dorm some moldy headgear says you have to sleep in." Tonks grinned, and Hermione nodded thoughtfully.

"Anyway, I'm going to give this one up as a bad job and dash. Can I ask you to keep this whole thing under your hat? Not my finest hour, and all..."

"I suppose, if that's what you want. You actually have been very helpful, and it was good to have someone to quiz against without feeling intimidated. Plus, if you've already graduated, it's not as if you technically broke any school rules, I suppose..." Tonks cackled in delight.

"Thanks, I'll owe you one. Be careful of that word, though…"

"Which?"

"'Technically'. Take it from me...once you start down the dark path of rule-dodgery, forever will it dominate your destiny…" she paraphrased, grinning. "Fortunately for me, Moody thinks it can make for better Aurors." Tonks winked, and Disapparated, and Hermione was left alone again with only an inexplicable foreboding for company.

o-o-o

It wasn't long after that other students - current students, this time - started joining Hermione in the compartment. All first years, as older students didn't seem to want to sit with first-years, nor did many first-years apparently have the courage to try to join a compartment with older children. Hermione found herself sharing a compartment with two twin sisters named Padma and Parvati, and a shy blond girl named Hannah.

A woman with cart came by early on selling sweets, and they'd each bought a couple, the others explaining the unfamiliar products to Hermione. While they snacked, they engaged in innocuous small talk which Hermione nevertheless found interesting, as much of it involved nuances of magical society that she hadn't yet picked up from her reading.

Even if Tonks hadn't meant it maliciously, the experience of her prank had made Hermione accept the premise that her study habits might be considered intimidating by some people, so rather than being entirely forthcoming, she'd decided to just wait and see what other people said. After several hours of chit-chat, it somehow hadn't come up, so she decided to try dropping it in herself, casually.

"So, have any of you read much of your school books yet?"

"A little, just to see" said Parvati, at the same time Padma said, "Some." They looked at each other, and Padma shrugged. "I got caught up in the Potions book, it's interesting."

"I thought I ought to wait until a Professor said what to read," said Hannah quietly. All three girls gave her quizzical looks. "Well, you know, some of our books were printed an awfully long time ago...what if the Professors give out corrections? I'd have ended up learning something wrong."

"That's...actually quite a good point," said Hermione, sounding surprised. The concept had never even occurred to her - she was used to getting fairly new textbooks from her school - but thinking about some of the publication dates she'd seen, she had to admit it was worth keeping in mind. Even under this mild praise, Hannah seemed to blossom.

"I do already know some herbology, though, my mum's quite good at it," she offered, smiling. "We've a garden at home, and she sells sometimes to the shops in Diagon Alley. What do your folks do?"

"Mum writes a recipes column for the Daily Prophet," said Parvati, "and dad is a curse-breaker for Gringotts," finished Padma. They looked to Hermione.

"Er, my parents are both dentists." Hannah nodded at this, while the twins looked confused. "People muggles go to when their teeth hurt, to fix them, or to help keep them clean," Hermione elaborated. They began to consider this apparently foreign concept, and Hermione noticed Padma was staring openly at her mouth. "There's a different sort that straighten people's teeth," she added with mild chagrin, lowering her face a bit and closing her lips to hide her front teeth.

There was an awkward silence for a moment, which was broken by a knock on the compartment door. Hermione leapt to her feet to open it, eager for a distraction. There was a round-faced boy outside, his cheeks a little wet.

"Excuse me, I've lost my toad...I just wondered if any of you had seen it?" Padma and Hanna wrinkled their noses, though Parvati looked sympathetic. They all shook their heads, however.

"I'm Parvati...what's your name?" Parvati asked gently.

"Oh, Neville. Neville Longbottom."

"When did you see it last?" asked Hermione. She'd wondered about that bit of the Letter that mentioned bringing animals, and had assumed it was like a witch's familiar. But while owls apparently shared a unique affinity with witches and wizards, displaying unusual (by muggle standards) intelligence and an apparently magical ability to navigate, Hermione hadn't read anything that suggested they (or cats, or toads) established any supernatural connection with the wizard that owned them. This seemed to be more evidence of that, otherwise presumably Neville could've used it to help find his pet.

"About an hour ago. I'd lost him earlier in getting settled on the train, but my gran found him for me," he said glumly.

"How'd she do that?" asked Padma.

"She used a Summoning Charm. But I don't know how to do anything yet, I only just got my wand." Hermione had seen references to the Summoning Charm in her reading, but the spell itself wasn't in any of her actual spellbooks. She supposed that meant it wasn't considered a Practical Household Charm, which was odd, as it seemed likely to be quite useful...maybe it was taught to everyone at Hogwarts, but later on than second year, which didn't bode well for trying to work it out themselves even if Neville did remember the incantation.

"Well, there must be plenty of older students on the train," Hermione said reasonably, "Since this is the last compartment, we'll just go back through in the other direction until we can find one who knows the spell." The boy nodded, looking pathetically grateful. She waved to the other girls and set off down the hallway with Neville in tow.

The first compartment she opened held a pair of boys, with messy and red hair respectively. The redhead was brandishing his wand, which made Hermione think it was at least worth asking, though she guessed they were also first-years, based on their size.

"Excuse me, do either of you know how to do a Summoning Charm? Neville's lost his toad," explained Hermione.

"Uh, no," said the redhead. "Think it goes 'achio' or something, mum does it all the time at home."

"All right, thanks. Sorry to interrupt. Were you about to practice a spell?" she asked with some enthusiasm, trying to be polite.

"Yeah…" He cleared his throat elaborately.

"Sunshine, daisies, butter mellow; Turn this stupid, fat rat yellow," he intoned, waving his wand imprecisely at the apparently sleeping - and unwell, if the condition of his fur was any indication - rat on his lap. Nothing happened, which did not surprise Hermione at all.

"You didn't get taught that spell by a girl named Mary Sue by any chance, did you?" she asked tentatively.

"What?" asked the redhead. "No. My brother, George. Probably wrong on purpose, he and Fred think they're Merlin reborn when it comes to pranking," he said, a bit glumly. Hermione narrowed her eyes.

"Are they in Gryffindor?" she asked. The boy nodded. Hermione sniffed sharply, then turned to Neville and said, "Sorry, just one second." She drew her wand, pointed it at the sleeping rat and said, "Colovaria!" The rat's fur obligingly turned bright yellow, and all the boys' mouths dropped open. "Just act perfectly normal," Hermione suggested, "when your brother sees him, he'll be trying to figure out how you got his silly made-up spell to actually work." She nodded in satisfaction, then turned to continue down the hallway. Neville shrugged helplessly, then followed.

"Who was that?", she heard the other boy ask from behind her as she walked, followed by the voice of the redhead, who said, "No clue, mate, but she's bloody brilliant - George'll go mental!" Hermione felt a bit guilty that what she'd done and suggested itself might count as a prank, but decided that there must be some pranking equivalent to the legal theory of justifiable self-defence, and let the warm glow of the offhanded compliment propel her onwards.

In short order, they managed to find a fifth year who had no problem (after Neville informed him the toad was named Trevor) Summoning him, to Neville's sincere gratitude. Hermione left Neville in his compartment with an admonition to keep a closer eye on Trevor, then made her way back towards her own compartment. Along the way, she had to press herself firmly against one wall to avoid being trampled by a trio of boys who pushed past without even acknowledging her, one of them whinging about probably having been poisoned by a diseased yellow rat. She decided this was probably not a coincidence, so she poked her head into the redhead's compartment.

"What happened?" she asked, observing their sweets had been scattered around a bit. "I was nearly bowled over by some boys running down the corridor - they, uh, seem to think your rat may be diseased." The two boys rolled back into their seats with laughter.

"Bloody perfect," said the redhead, wiping away a tear and lifting the rat up by his tail to examine him. "Seems like he's all right - just sleeping again, if you can believe it. Anyway, what was all that about, sounded like Malfoy'd already met you?" he asked the messy-haired boy. The other boy described a brief but unpleasant interaction with someone Hermione rather wished Tonks'd had the opportunity to 'deflate'.

"Yeah, my dad's told me about that lot. Came running back after You-Know-Who vanished, claimed they were bewitched, but my dad thinks it's bol-" he glanced at Hermione, "er, rubbish. Anyway," he said, turning to Hermione, "that's two I owe you, if Malfoy's mate thinks Scabbers' given him Yellow Fever or some such. I'm Ron Weasley, this here's Harry Potter."

"Hermione Granger," she offered. "And you're welcome." She paused for a moment, then asked Harry, "The Harry Potter?" He nodded, a bit uncomfortably. "Goodness...you're in several of the books I got for extra reading, but it never occurred to me you'd be here at all, much less in my year. I really ought to have done the math."

"I'm...in books?" he asked, somewhat taken aback.

"Yes, but it's all very complimentary," Hermione said, trying to reassure him. She couldn't imagine what that felt like, and thought it a bit odd as well that he seemed not to know about it, since he'd had ten or so years to learn to cope. But then the books really said nothing at all about what had happened to the baby after somehow impossibly saving Britain - and arguably the world - by virtue of being mysteriously invincible. Clearly there was more to his story, but she couldn't think of a casual way to ask, and there wasn't really time anyway. "Anyway, you two ought to change, the train's slowing so we must be quite close. I'll see you at the Sorting," she said, then left to return to her own compartment, closing the door behind her.

o-o-o-o-o

A/N: So, I had this brilliant plan wherein Hermione would meet seventh-year Tonks, and she'd become her mentor through first year and there'd be hi-jinx aplenty. Halfway through writing, I did my belated due diligence and discovered Tonks graduated the year before Hermione started.

Awkward, but I'll work that out. In any case, I decided to leave it in as just a cameo, with a little tweaking. Someday (possibly when I get an editor) I'll learn how to throw away something I've written, but for now, you'll have to pry my little fantasies out of my cold, dead hard drive.

Chapter 6.1: Interlude - Dubius

Author's Note: Sorry for the long hiatus, I had some cause to question my motives for writing, and it took a great deal of thought before I felt I could continue. I'd written this interlude previously, but I hope to come back with additional chapters in the next month or two.

Disclaimer time - I've read (and love) Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality; it's actually what gave me the kick to start my own fic. While there's bound to be some overlap - since both contain muggle science and a 'genuinely smart' Hermione - I'm deliberately making some different choices about how magic 'works', and keeping almost all the other characters essentially canon, in the hopes of steering things away from just being a rehash of the same themes. I've no desire to re-write HPMOR...I seriously doubt I could improve upon it. (N.B. - Be cautious in taking that as a recommendation to read it - while it's very well written and terribly funny at times, it also goes to some shockingly dark places.)

Of course, there's an issue with Hermione using 'genuine' intelligence while no one else changes, though - quite often the answer to questions along the lines of, "Why did character A not simply X or Y or Z, were they just dumb?" is that if they had, the story would've been much shorter (or, from another perspective, much harder to write well). For the purposes of this fic, I'm just going to play those things where they lie. Even if some canon issues end up resolved 'early', there will be logical repercussions and consequences that I hope will keep things interesting. That said, I've no illusions that I'm writing a masterpiece, here - I'm having fun so far, hopefully you are too!

o-o-o-o-o

Interlude - Dubius

Albus Dumbledore waited calmly as all but one of the Professors and staff filed out of his office. Once they'd gone, Professor McGonagall took a seat in front of his desk - the meeting that had just concluded had not been long, and no one had been seated. Only then did he settle into his own chair.

"So, Minerva. I presume, by your request to remain, that you've objections you wanted to voice in private?" the Headmaster asked, mildly.

"A murder, at Hogwarts. A murder, at Hogwarts," she repeated, with emphasis. The woman paused, as if unsure how to continue.

"Which implies a murderer, of course. And while it is not clear how much time the culprit had before Madam Pomfrey was discovered, I nevertheless sealed Hogwarts against exit - possibly trapping a murderer inside with us...and our students," he prompted, calmly.

"So, you understand my consternation, then?"

"I do." He waited. While he would not typically begrudge an explanation to one who had a right to it, the demands on his time were...considerable. It was a fact of his existence that he could avoid a great many uncomfortable conversations with a subtle reminder of the trust he had earned, by virtue of being both talented and right, on many occasions. It was pure reputation, and he was not above using it...sometimes, that alone was enough to forestall objections and allow him to get on with the actual work.

"And yet, you've done it anyway. Nor have you summoned Aurors. And you're going to allow everyone to believe this was Poppy's...negligence," she persisted. Apparently, this was not to be one of those times.

"You know what is being guarded here, and what the consequences could be if it fell into the wrong hands. If this incident is not related - and for the moment it is unclear how it would be - every additional witch or wizard admitted would be another potential avenue for exploitation...even Aurors. Whereas I have every faith in the staff's ability to locate and subdue Madam Pomfrey's assailant."

"What about the students?"

"The lengths to which the murderer went to make it appear a tragic accident strongly suggest an interest in remaining unnoticed - it seems unlikely they would take further rash action without waiting to ensure their subterfuge was successful, and thus the students should be in no danger for some period. And in regards to that subterfuge, I believe Poppy would not begrudge a temporary besmirching of her reputation, in the interests of seeing justice served."

"Albus, we're not trained for this," McGonagall insisted, frustrated.

"Neither are murderers, by and large, yet they do succeed in their grim work with alarming frequency. Should we, who have the advantage of a noble cause, expect any less of ourselves?" Dumbledore knew how this sort of thing sounded when he said it - a mixture of inscrutable wisdom and hopeless naivete. It made it difficult for most people to debate against him, particularly those who respected him; the inscrutability and his reputation made them worry they'd seem a fool for arguing later, the naivete as if they'd be kicking a puppy. Sure enough, Minerva got that look on her face that said she had in no way conceded the argument and yet was at a loss to continue it.

For a moment, as occasionally happened, Dumbledore felt an urge to tell her his entire plan, or even all his plans. It grew lonely at times, having no one to confide in. But while there were obvious advantages of security in plans no one knew about, they held a subtler virtue as well. If you only revealed the successful plans, after the fact...your apparent success rate became, well, startlingly impressive.

The urge passed, as it always did.

"Was there anything else?"

"Actually, there was one other matter. There's a first year who requires additional supervision in Transfiguration - Hermione Granger."

"Ah. Another Moira?" the wizard asked slowly, his face for a moment showing every year of its age.

"No...I caught it early, thank Merlin, and she appears to understand the seriousness of the matter. Though she seems even brighter than Moira was, which makes things both better and worse."

"Very well. Keep me informed, but as always I will leave such matters to your judgement." McGonagall nodded, her expression equal parts grim and satisfied, though her eyes held a hint of pity as well. She strode out of his office.

Once she'd gone, Dumbledore seemed to deflate a bit, the imposing and confident arch-wizard somehow replaced by an old man, tired and uncertain. There were downsides to his penchant for plotting, of course, chief among them the necessity that he alone bore the burdens of the damage from plans that failed, and often even of those that succeeded.

He sat, slumped, for some time.

Chapter 10: a Poor Sort of Memory

A/N: I wrote this entire chapter one way, set it aside, wrote it again in an entirely different plot direction, then once more in a third. This is the second, and best (I think). I don't know if this is how authors normally work, but throwing away writing is painful. Still, it's hard to argue with the results (unless this chapter is rubbish, I suppose, then it's easy).

Edit: Thanks to monstrousbird from r/rational for the Britpick on "bleachers"!

o-o-o-o-o

Chapter 10 - "...a Poor Sort of Memory…"

Hermione did not wake, per se - she simply found herself to be not asleep. She was no longer in the Library… In point of fact, for a moment she wasn't certain where she was, so unfamiliar was the scene, though the general architectural style suggested she was somewhere in Hogwarts. Many people moved about, a few with urgent speed, but most slowly, bearing obvious injuries or a deep weight of sorrow. No one paid any attention to her whatsoever. It was the ceiling that made her realize this was the Great Hall, its powerful enchantment showing the dark, star-filled sky beyond, streaked with smoke and flashes of strange magical after-effects.

But the tables and seats were all gone, save a couple turned onto their sides as makeshift barricades. Many of the people present stood or knelt over wounded, or even-

Hermione tried to grasp what she was seeing. One of the Weasley Twins was lying terribly still, and beside him, her face and hair unmistakeable, Tonks, the Hufflepuff from the train. Her unmoving hand was clasped in the hand of an unfamiliar man, equally lifeless. What she could only presume was the rest of the Weasley family was crying over the dead boy - except he wasn't a boy… Even prone, it was obvious the Twin - and it bothered Hermione a great deal that she wasn't sure which one - was even taller than she remembered, sturdier...adult. Tonks too, for that matter, though it was less obvious from the position of her...her b-

Hermione started to walk closer, solemn but desperate to understand, but stopped in her tracks. Another young brunette woman - who had been embracing one of the Weasleys - had turned her head slightly to face Hermione. For a bizarre moment, she thought it was her mother. But she was too young, and there were differences here and there. In fact, now that she thought about it, the woman actually looked more like-

The Great Hall went dark and swimmy.

o-o-o

She was in a strangely decorated living room, cramped and a little cluttered - from the slightly askew style, she presumed it was a Wizarding home, but very comfortable, for all that. There were a bunch of adults, and young adults, standing in a rough circle, each holding aloft a small glass of liquid, all swirls of rich amber and orange.

"Mad-Eye," said a flame-haired man, and everyone else repeated it. Including both Weasley Twins, and Tonks, looking very much alive but distraught, and from the scar and glasses what was clearly an older and much more put-together Harry Potter, along with an equally older but still not-terribly-put-together-looking Ron, and that same woman who she was almost certain was-

"Mad-Eye," added the Groundskeeper, Mr. Hagrid, with a maudlin hiccough. The room went dark and swimmy.

o-o-o

She was outdoors, near a small cottage. There were people standing near an oddly tiny grave. She was just close enough to the edge to make out the caricatured features of a house-elf, a woolen hat crammed onto his head. The strange older Harry and Ron were there - Harry looking devastated, Ron looking awkward in bare feet. His arm was around a brunette in a dressing gown, looking an absolute mess, her hair everywhere, her eyes puffy and reddened from tears, her face terribly pale. There was also a young blonde woman in a coat, looking a little disheveled, another thin blonde woman in an apron who was somehow almost offensively pretty, and the orange-haired man who'd started the toast in the previous...whatever was going on-

"Good-bye, Dobby", said Harry, terribly quietly.

The unnamed-but-probably-Weasley gave a solemn wave of his wand and a nearby pile of earth gracefully filled the grave, piling up to slightly above the level of the ground, and the scene went dark and swimmy.

o-o-o

She was in her parents' living room. They were sitting beside each other on the sofa, and staring almost directly at her, but they didn't seem to see her, or indeed anything.

"Mum? Dad?" Hermione, alarmed, waved a hand before their eyes, even leaned forward and poked her mother's knee, but there was no response whatsoever. It was quiet enough in the room that she could hear their breathing, and nothing else. But something made her turn her head, and in the doorway to the kitchen, out of their line of sight, the woman from the Great Hall, who kept drawing Hermione's attention, was casting spells on them, and she was using Hermione's wand or one that looked unreasonably like it, which pretty much clinched her impossible suspicions if she was willing to accept them.

The woman wasn't saying anything aloud, just making gesture after gesture, complicated swoops and curls and nested twists that Hermione could barely follow, let alone identify. But she finished with a very simple gesture, one Hermione did recognize, and a single word, rough with emotion but precisely enunciated.

"Obliviate."

Hermione lunged forward to try to shield her parents, but the spell somehow ignored her, and the room went dark and swimmy.

o-o-o

She was in a room she didn't recognize, but it was very finely appointed in a Wizarding way, all crystal and mahogany and tapestries. There were various people standing about - a hunched little man with a silver hand, a much taller man wearing a ragged fur coat who had strangely stretched - almost bestial - features. A trio of mutually light-haired people stood close to each other, a man and a woman and an older boy, who - despite his inexplicable age - was quite recognizably Draco Malfoy...looking not appalled, exactly, but neither entirely sanguine.

But all eyes in the room, Hermione's included, were focused on the last two people present. A woman in a tattered black dress, somehow both beautiful and sickly at the same time, her hair black and wild, eyes crazed and fixed with her wand towards the same young woman from the Great Hall, dirty and disheveled in casual clothes, her face terribly pale and streaked with tears.

"What else did you take, what else? ANSWER ME! CRUCIO!" shrieked the dark-haired witch, and the younger woman writhed under the Unforgivable Curse, releasing a horrible extended scream, which broke only just long enough to draw enough breath to begin the scream anew.

Hermione couldn't bear it and turned away, covering her ears with her hands, and she could still hear it. But mercifully, after a moment, the screaming - her screaming - faded away as the room went dark and swimmy.

o-o-o

She was on the grounds of Hogwarts, near the Great Lake, beside a white marble table. Dozens, hundreds of chairs faced it, in neat rows. So many people, many she didn't recognize, but a few she did. All the school staff, a great many students, the grown versions of which she was starting to find familiar, including herself. Her other-self's face was streaked with silent tears quite different from the ones she'd just seen. There were centaurs present, and Mr. Hagrid was at the back, next to a giant, and Hermione wondered what that was about, but at the same time she knew she was deliberately focusing on irrelevant details, the implications of the sombre mood and arrangements were obvious even without the benefit of her earlier...whatever-they-were's…

Hermione forced herself to look at the table, and saw the Headmaster's body. Even as shock struck deeply into her, she wondered how it could have happened - he wasn't that old by Wizarding standards and he was widely acknowledged as the most talented wizard in Britain, if not the world. As she watched, uncomprehendingly, the table erupted in shockingly intense white flames, though even as close as Hermione stood, they seemingly gave off no heat, and there were screams of startlement from within the attending crowd. The blinding fire rose higher and higher, until there was no sign of the body, or indeed the table. But as quickly as they'd started, the flames vanished, and only a white marble tomb was left behind.

The gathering went dark and swimmy.

o-o-o

She was on a small grassy clearing, at the edge of what seemed to be a large hedge maze. Facing it were a large set of seats set in stands, packed full of people. Most were too far away to make out, though she could vaguely recognize herself, sitting next to Ron.

Directly before her was Harry Potter, still looking older than he ought to, but not nearly so much as before. He was clutching a shining trophy of some sort in one hand, while his other was latched firmly around another boy she didn't recognize, perhaps a couple years older than Harry - this Harry, rather.

Harry looked dazed and pale, his left leg was bleeding badly, and his right arm nearly as much. The other boy bore various small injuries, but his eyes stared sightlessly. The Headmaster was leaning over them, alive, obviously, but his face ashen.

Harry released the trophy and grabbed Professor Dumbledore's wrist, not releasing the other boy's body. He still seemed dazed, but he pulled his face close to the Headmaster's and whispered with a fearful intensity.

"He's back. He's back. Voldemort."

Everything went dark and swimmy.

o-o-o

She was in the hospital wing. She was lying on the floor, facing the ceiling, and a young woman in healer's robes was leaning over her with a concerned expression, her wand out. Nurse Wainscott?

"Mobilicorpus," said the nurse, and Hermione felt her body grow light and drift up from where she'd apparently collapsed to the floor. She glided easily over to one of the beds and drifted gently down upon it.

Hermione, fearing the worst, looked around anxiously to discover who was dead now. But the other beds were empty of bodies, living or otherwise, there was no one else here other than the healer.

"Wait," she murmured. "Something is...you can see me...you can hear me?" Madam Wainscott nodded, her expression uncertain but reassuring.

"Yes, just relax, take slow, deep breaths. You apparently got here just in time. I should've been faster to get you into a bed, but...does anything hurt, did you hit your head when you fell? Revelo volnus." This last was murmured as she waved her wand over Hermione's body from head to toes. Hermione didn't feel any pain, though her head felt a bit foggy, as if she'd just woken up from an uneasy sleep. Sleep.

"Something put me to sleep," Hermione said, suddenly. "Something possessing me, a ghost, maybe? But then I saw...I don't know what...visions of horrible things...I think of the future. People dying, maybe me dying...You-Know-Who coming back...and I was always there...older me, I mean..." Her voice dropped a bit as she continued, mostly to herself, "I really ought to have read more about Divination, but most of the books implied it was extremely unreliable at best…" Madam Wainscott nodded, as if what Hermione had said were the most normal thing in the world.

"Yes. None of it was real, only a nightmare, best just not to think about it at all…" she said, in a tone that Hermione had come to recognize from adults, one which she - ever so slightly - loathed. She tried to sit up angrily in the bed, but light pressure from the nurse's hand against her shoulder was sufficient to make this impossible - she must still be a little weak, shaking off the sleep.

"No. I'm not sick, this is important," she insisted, trying to make her voice stern in lieu of whatever confidence came from being upright. "Something is happening to me, and horrible things are going to happen...it's not a hallucination, it's…" she trailed off for a moment, realizing she still wasn't entirely sure it wasn't a hallucination. What if she did have a brain tumor or something? "There's a note, in my bag, upside down...it says things…" Though Hermione once again remembered that the cryptic notes had been in her own handwriting, and wouldn't really constitute evidence of anything one way or another - even to herself, if she were honest about it.

"Do you...what is the last thing you remember?" asked the nurse, looking...concerned, but not exactly alarmed.

"I'd been in the Library, studying, then I saw these strange notes appear - or re-appear, I think - on the bottom of the parchment, and I was trying to understand them and I had some sort of...memory isn't exactly right, but I don't know what to call it, and I thought I might be possessed and I should tell an adult, but then it put me to sleep on my way out of the Library. I saw a bunch of horrible things, mostly people being dead, and then I woke up here." Madam Wainscott's eyebrows rose, but she still didn't look as alarmed as Hermione thought she ought to. Come to think of it, Hermione herself no longer felt that strange sense of alarm that had affected her so strongly in the Library when she'd announced her intention to tell someone.

"You don't remember hearing a spell cast on you, or walking here, or speaking with me?" Hermione blinked.

"I...no. What?" The nurse turned a bit, examining the labels on a variety of potion bottles on a rack against the wall as she spoke.

"You walked in just a few minutes ago. You said that you'd heard someone - you didn't see who - cast a spell on you…'Confundo Oraculum Maximo', and you weren't sure what it had done but your head 'felt peculiar', so you came here, and explained, and then you collapsed before I could get you into a bed."

"I said…? But...that's not right…"

"'Confundo Oraculum' is a nasty variation on the Confundus Charm, called the 'Seer's Hex'," explained Madam Wainscott as she turned back to Hermione, a bottle in her off hand. "It makes you convinced you can see the future, you see, as well as fogging your thoughts and memories around to prompt you to see things you want, or more often, fear. Normally it the certainty fades away of its own accord in an hour or two, along with most of the 'visions'. But that Maximo makes it something quite beyond that, I don't even know the name and I...ah...don't know the proper countercurse, assuming, hopefully, there is one...I'll have to do some reading and consult the Professors." The young woman was clearly trying to portray confidence, but she couldn't hide a bit of nervousness. "Honestly, I'd just use a Forgetting Charm, but-"

"No!" shouted Hermione, and this time she was able to push herself up, sliding back in the bed away from the nurse. She made a calming motion, which, given it was with her wand hand, did not reassure Hermione in the slightest.

"Easy, Miss Granger, easy. I was just saying I can't Obliviate you because that sort of magic doesn't interact well - or safely - with Confunding effects. And the effects are lasting, but the spell itself isn't sustained, so there's no point in a Finite. If we can't find a specific countercurse, well, you may just have to do your best to put all this out of your mind."

Hermione stared at her as if she were insane, and immediately recognized the irony in that thought. Either way, getting angrier and pointing out how impossible a task she'd casually suggested probably wouldn't help. And she still wasn't sure what to think...if she was possessed, it actually sounded like a rather clever story to discredit anything she might say afterward - the only confusing flaw in that was that it had discouraged the nurse from just making her forget the whole thing. On the other hand, if schizophrenia or something was the problem, it was a way for the illness to conceal itself, by steering her away from proper care, and preventing her aberrant thoughts from simply being removed. It still seemed implausible that she could be having these sorts of rational thoughts about it if she were mentally unwell, but, again, it's not as if she really knew what it would feel like from the inside.

"All right," she began, trying to make her voice calm. "Is there some way you could verify that I'm not possessed by a ghost or something? Just...you know...for my peace of mind?" Madam Wainscott frowned, then tucked the potion bottle away in a pocket of her apron and moved a few beds down to crouch by a short two-level bookshelf, running her finger over the spines. As she did so, Hermione opened her bag - its strap still over her shoulder - and began pulling out her notes. Not furtively, but matter-of-factly, as if it should be of no concern to anyone, particularly a nurse. The woman did glance at her, but only briefly before continuing to peruse the books.

Hermione flipped through the thick sheaf of pages quickly, looking for the tell-tale sign of mutually inverted sections of handwriting, but didn't see the page. She frowned and went back through more slowly, then stopped. She'd found the page, all right, but it held only her notes on potential library magic, and there was no sign of the mysterious additional lines. Option A - that never happened, and I just imagined it, equal evidence of mental illness or an oddly specific and aggressive Confundus. Option B - something is possessing me, and after putting me to sleep, it just used a spell to wipe those lines off the page. Hermione scowled and shoved the notes back into her bag, with slightly more force than was strictly necessary.

Nurse Wainscott returned, holding a pair of books. She'd clearly noticed Hermione putting her papers away, but chose not to remark upon it, about which Hermione was both grateful and slightly irritated. Instead, the woman set the books down, holding one open to a page marked with a thin blue ribbon, and began casting a series of spells from them over Hermione, many which included the words spiritus or effigia, and once, usurpator. As the nurse flipped from page to page, switching books halfway through, Hermione tried to memorize each spell as best she could, but some of the gestures were not ones she recognized at all, and a couple spells had been cast non-verbally. Though at least one of the gestures seemed familiar from the extended prelude to the spell her older self had...would?...might?...cast on her parents. Was that evidence of anything, that she'd seen an apparently real spell element she had no way of knowing?

Maybe...but maybe a sufficiently strong Confundus can actually impart some information that the caster knows and the victim doesn't, and it sounds like a strong caster would've been required. But why would an upper-year student do such a thing to me anyway? Bullying - her books had said - was a complex dance of status and dominance, and tended to operate within narrow age ranges. A child might well torment significantly younger children out of pure sadism, but that was supposedly rare. Much more often victims would be children sufficiently younger or weaker than the the bully to be vulnerable, but still close enough to their age that the bully wouldn't lose status among their own peers by attacking too weak an opponent.

"Well, after all that, I'm quite positive there's nothing in your head that didn't originate from your own mind," said Madam Wainscott suddenly, breaking Hermione's gloomy train of thought. "Though that does include whatever your mind invented based on the Confundus, of course." She put her hand on Hermione's shoulder sympathetically. "I hope that does make you feel a little better?" Hermione considered the question, and upon reflection, it didn't. At all.

"I appreciate you checking for me," said the Ravenclaw, with carefully true wording. "So...what now? May I go...at least until you find a countercurse, I suppose?" The nurse shook her head, once again withdrawing the potion she'd held before.

"It's clear you're still suffering secondary ill effects from such a strong hex, so I'd prefer you got more rest. And it may help in another way - I have a potion to allow dreamless sleep. It should ensure you get good quality sleep, but it should also make your memories of the hex less distinct, and help you put them aside?" Hermione was a bit surprised to hear that witches apparently knew about memory consolidation during REM sleep, but she supposed the proper magic ought to be able to tell you as much or more about what was happening in someone's head as an EEG or MRI machine. It's not as if science had any reliable ways of making people forget things, and magic apparently had several.

"Okay," Hermione said, with a slight sigh.

"I'll make sure you're excused from classes for the rest of the day-"

"I don't have any left today," interrupted Hermione.

"Oh, well, good. But I'll still inform your Professors and the Headmaster of the incident, so they can be properly accommodating if you have any...er...lingering issues."

"That's...really not necessary," Hermione objected, warily. If she does that, then effectively everyone I might go to will have a plausible excuse to not believe a single thing I say about any of this…

"It's no trouble, and it's school policy anyway - I must. I'm sure they will want to go to some lengths to discover who hexed you in any case, it's a bit beyond the normal sort of student shenanigans." Hermione nodded. It wasn't as if she could stop her. "I'll fetch you a set of pyjamas and let you change so you're more comfortable, and then you can take the potion - you should sleep clear through to tomorrow morning." Nurse Wainscott did as she'd said, altering the apparently generic pyjamas with a few quick spells so they properly fit Hermione, then pulling the curtains around her bed and withdrawing to let her change.

Hermione made enough of a production out of removing her robes to hopefully mask the sound of also fetching a quill, blank parchment and her wand from her bag. A general Silencing Charm was far beyond her, but she leveled her wand at the quill and parchment in turn, adding a whispered Quietus for each, then gingerly tested one against the other, and nodded in satisfaction as the normally quiet scratch was nearly inaudible.

Hermione quickly began to transcribe everything she could remember about everything that had happened starting with the Library - including as faithful a reproduction as she could of the missing notes - alternating hands so she could awkwardly continue to undress and change while she did so. When she'd finished - after going back and adding a quick note at the top - she took up her wand again and whispered Impervius at each page, folded them in half, then again firmly crosswise. She hesitated for a moment, second guessing herself, but then followed through with her hopefully-not-mad plan. She cast one final spell at the bundle, then flung the tight square of parchment directly out of the partially open window behind the bed.

Immediately, the "sourceless" irrational panic from the Library flooded back into her, and her hands shook as she put everything back into her bag and then climbed into the hospital bed. But even as her nerves betrayed her, she steadfastly pushed them down and essayed a wavering smile, equal parts uncertainty and grim determination. The return of the feeling was a tiny piece of evidence, and Hermione was choosing to interpret it as progress, rather than mental illness. If she wasn't sane, well, this shouldn't do any harm. If she was...

"Nurse Wainscott? I'm ready for the potion now," she said, loudly. But before the woman had reached the curtain around Hermione's bed, she lowered her voice and in an almost inaudibly soft whisper - yet somehow simultaneously full of iron - added two more words.

"Your move."

Chapter 14: Lavatorial Correspondence

Hermione did not rush back to Ravenclaw Tower after the memorial, though she did not dawdle either - it was nearly curfew. A couple of groups of older Ravens were making their way back in the same direction, talking quietly. Roger Davies was walking alone, looking morose. Hermione would've liked to say something to him, distract him a bit, but given the mood she was in, she wasn't sure she could keep herself from blurting out what she suspected about Madam Pomfrey's death. And despite her newfound determination to do something about it, she still wouldn't do anything precipitous without trying to get a better understanding of the consequences from her older self. So she just measured her pace so as to stay behind him, out of his view, and felt quietly bad about it.

As she walked, she tried to decide what her criteria were going to be for acting or not acting, depending on what she learned. When Hermione read fiction, she'd begun to mildly prefer science fiction over fantasy after the age of five or so, when her critical thinking skills had developed to the point of distraction. But in either genre she'd encountered various ideas on the "stubbornness" of changing timelines, in fictional worlds where that was even possible. The mysterious notes had mentioned the term "backlash", which rather implied some consequence. If there was somehow some guaranteed moral consequence that outweighed apprehending a murderer and getting justice for Madam Pomfrey, like someone random dying, or some other murderer going free, obviously she wouldn't choose that. If it was a personal consequence, like her dying...Hermione liked to think she was the sort of person who would give her life to save another, but that sort of thing tended to happen in the moment, in emergencies - she suspected it would be much harder to do in a premeditated way. And she couldn't help wondering about the ultimate outcomes - if she could save more people later, by not dying...but she wasn't at all sure if that line of thinking was morally defensible or just rationalization.

But that was all in the event Older Hermione could convince her that there were guaranteed consequences, and Hermione wasn't sure how likely that was. Given how Time ought to work, with cause and effect still intact even if effects sometimes now preceded causes...either changing Time ought to be simply impossible, because things happening other than the way in which they'd already been observed to happen was just upending the definition of the word "happen", or if the universe was a many-worlds sort, changing Time ought to be utterly unpredictable, with any significant change causing uncountable knock-on changes down the line, some of which might be good and some of which might be bad. But the existence of magic sort of threw those theories into disarray, because now things that weren't organic were allowed to somehow have agency of a sort...Accio, and wands, and Hogwarts itself. Who was to say that fundamental parts of reality couldn't as well? Or - far more to her liking - that there was some hidden metaphysical principle that stabilized Time in a universe that allowed it to be fiddled with, but which might nevertheless be understood if you worked at it? And neither of those theories explained the references to "erasing" a person, which implied that someone had been removed from Time, but in some way that people still remembered them, or how would anyone realize in the first place, and that didn't seem to make any logical sense at all.

By the time she reached the tower, she hadn't come to any particular conclusions - there were still too many things she didn't understand about the situation. And now she had to pay attention to figuring out the mechanics of her "conversation". Most of the Ravenclaws were curious by nature, so just sitting in the common room or her bedroom and repeatedly taking small doses of a potion interspersed by bouts of writing - and possibly visibly nodding off for some length of time - seemed bound to attract questions. She could try to do it under the covers, but she didn't think she could manage to avoid exciting notice that way either. It'd have to be the dorm bathroom - there were three stalls and three tubs for five girls (Hermione had no experience with boarding school, and did not realize how luxurious this was), so even if she took a long time in one stall it wouldn't cause serious problems, and if anyone asked she could just say she was having stomach problems, which was still true. In the end she went ahead with that plan, and added a decision to wait until the rest of her dorm-mates were settling down to sleep to make disruptions even less likely.

It hadn't been mentioned in Madam Wainscott's instructions, but while she was waiting for everyone to go to sleep, Hermione managed to find some references to Liquid Sheep in the Tower Library, and there didn't seem to be a minimum effective dose. So she'd just take two drops in water at first and see how far that got her, extending it if necessary. Possibly also decreasing the amount of water gradually, or the fact that she was doing this in a bathroom would become convenient for inconvenient reasons. She had realized, of course, that if her other self was inclined to, this plan would allow her to just take more drops and extend her own control indefinitely, but she'd already demonstrated she could put Hermione to sleep if she wanted, so it didn't seem like too much of a risk.

Finally, everyone seemed to be settled. Hermione, in her nightgown, slipped as quietly out of bed as she could, fetched all her materials - which she'd taken the precaution of placing into a toiletries bag in advance - then padded into the bathroom. She filled one of the common water pitchers from the sink and took it with her into a stall. Perched carefully on a toilet seat, stall door firmly closed and latched, she wrote out her opening argument.

I'm presuming from what I've already seen that you can see and hear everything I do. If that's not the case, please correct me, and I'll be more verbose, but for the moment, I'm going to continue. I am strongly opposed to letting the matter of M.P. go unaddressed, and in a lesser sense, all the various other similar things that haven't happened yet - which come to think of it I'm not sure you know I know about, since I didn't "see" them per se - what happen(ed/s) to one of the W.T, T the colorful Hufflepuff, and the scruffy man, D the house elf, "M.E", P.D., and the student with H when he talked about V, plus what you did to our parents. I understand there are dangers involved in Time, but it's not illegal for you to talk about it with me anymore since I already know, or at least not more illegal than you not turning me in, in any case - and yourself, since I learned about it from you. So I need you to explain to me your reasons for thinking it better to not do anything - and please, do so assuming I'm capable of understanding, which I ought not to need to mention since you're me, but I honestly am not as sure of your judgement as I might've expected to be under the circumstances.

Hermione reviewed what she'd written, poured a half glass of water, then carefully measured two drops of Liquid Sheep into it and stirred thoroughly. She put everything but the quill and paper down, and held the latter firmly under her hands on her lap, leaning back carefully so hopefully she wouldn't slide or fall as she fell asleep - she wasn't sure if her other self would be able to take over quickly enough. Hermione took a deep breath, let it out, then downed the glass in a couple of gulps. She set the glass on the floor and reached into her bag to extract her watch - a lovely silver spring-wound one her parents had purchased for her when Hermione's early reading had revealed that digital watches wouldn't work properly at Hogwarts - to check the time, then put it back down.

It took a bit longer than she'd expected - maybe because she was using a smaller dose - but soon Hermione felt her eyelids growing impossibly heavy, her thoughts warm and foggy, and then for a time she thought nothing.

o-o-o

When her eyes opened again, she didn't feel particularly groggy, and there was extra writing on the paper. But first things first. She checked her watch - ten minutes, minus maybe three for falling asleep, which was good...even if she had to spend all night she should get at least 50 exchanges, minus a bit for any time she took reading, thinking and writing her own responses. Only after that was taken care of did she read the response.

First, I have to apologize for all of this, sincerely. It isn't precisely my fault - though I ought to have been able to prevent it - but it's definitely not your fault. I can understand the mildly antagonistic attitude you've had towards me, and under the circumstances I can't blame you. You seem a lot more persistent and capable than I remember myself being at your age, but then I had less serious problems to deal with, at least at first. In any case, please believe me when I say that I only want to do what's best for everyone - you included - given what's already happened. I'm going to explain everything I think I can as part of that...there's not a lot of time for anything else at this point.

Second, the odious T.N. is entirely correct, more than he knows. No matter what happens in this conversation, no matter what you decide, I implore you not to give any further hint to anyone that you know anything relating to V other than what an intelligent first-year might read on her own (and obviously, destroy these notes after we're done, but I hope that had been your plan already). Even to any Professors. There is an Art called Legilimency, known - among others - to some former and current D.E., which allows a very skilled witch to read someone else's thoughts. You should also try not to bring such things to mind when you're around other people, particularly not while making eye contact. And yes, I know that will be harder now that I've mentioned it, but there are techniques - look up Occlumency. It's going to take a very long time to learn without a good instructor or someone to practice against - and Hogwarts isn't likely to make one available to you for years without you explaining why you need it - so I suggest getting started now. But Occlumency skills are not common even amongst adults, so anything you reveal could thus be traced back to you, even if an otherwise responsible person fully intended to keep your secrets carefully.

Third, you do not - or at least I did not - turn 'evil' at some point in the future. What I did for our parents was to protect them, it was almost certainly necessary, and everything was fixed later. Please take that into account when evaluating my moral compass. I am not sure what's going on with O. - I don't approve of what he did to you, but I've known him to be a moral person, and it seems all wandmakers are a bit peculiar, so I'm inclined to give him the benefit of the doubt for now. Try not to hold it against Memory Charms in general - yes, they can be used in abusive ways, but likewise the opposite - like almost any magic, they are a tool, and any moral weight comes entirely from the user.

So, on to actual arguments. Meddling with Time is dangerous in two ways. First, the H.R.C. (on which the T.T. is based) works in a very specific way, which is actually in some sense consistent with the muggle laws of physics. You haven't read it yet, but owl your parents to get you a copy of an issue of Physical Review D from last year - 42 (6) - the paper you're looking for is "Cauchy problem in spacetimes with closed timelike curves" - I looked it up myself, years later, for various reasons. The gist is, for areas of space-time where the future and the past are allowed to interact, no physical solution is possible which is not self-consistent (i.e. you can't "cause" anything retroactively that wasn't going to have happened already, there are no "changes"). A naive person might think that makes it safe, but it really, really doesn't. The end result of a situation like that is that if you try to change something, you are going to fail, you just can't necessarily predict how or why. The normal laws of probability don't apply, because any ostensibly possible outcome where you make a change isn't possible anymore, and thus all the otherwise unlikely things that are left get "promoted" to inconveniently likely indeed. Think about it, I'm sure you can imagine some examples.

Even then, in practice these events tend to be more unpleasant - even fatal - than you'd expect from appropriately adjusted random chance, which is why they're called "backlash". The stock explanation you get in the Ministry T.T. pamphlet is that Time doesn't like meddling, and "punishes" people for trying it. Myself, I think it might just be a sum over lifetime probabilities...if you're the kind of person to try it in the first place, one very unlikely event that nips things in the bud right off - by killing you or scaring you sufficiently - is actually more likely overall than a combined series of slightly implausible events that are forced to keep you from succeeding over and over again. But regardless of the explanation, backlashes are verifiable, and well-documented.

Now, as you've no doubt just objected while reading the first part, none of that may necessarily apply here, because changes have already happened, plus you've read the anecdotes about Erasure. This is where I get onto less solid ground, but that'll have to be in the next response, because you're starting to wake up, and I'm honestly not sure what would happen if I took more Liquid Sheep while I'm the one steering - better to stick with your protocol.

It was her own handwriting again, and it sounded like her. She hadn't been certain about her theories, but this did seem like confirmation. Unless it was someone else successfully pretending to be her, which given the whole mind-reading thing she'd just been informed about was actually more likely than she'd have thought previously. But if that were the case, then whoever it was ought not to have told her about it, since it made her more likely to question it. Unless that was just to establish trust and help sell the ruse…

Hermione frowned and abandoned the train of thought. She decided to set aside theories of deception unless something specifically made them seem more likely, since it was clear she couldn't logic her way to a conclusion without some actual evidence - and she'd read The Princess Bride.

The bit about the Hour Reversal Charm seemed to make sense, though Hermione wasn't sure what happened to free will in a universe like that. While she certainly could imagine an infinite number of ways for attempts to change the past to fail "coincidentally", there were certain self-referential situations that didn't seem to fit...like seeing a future version of yourself doing something, and then deciding quite specifically not to...what would then make you do it? Maybe you simply couldn't make that decision, because any situation in which you would have actually decided to wouldn't have been allowed to happen in the "first place" - you just wouldn't have cast the spell for some reason in the future.

And the last bit was also correct, in that Hermione had immediately noticed the HRC part was instructive but not relevant, since - at least from Older Hermione's perspective - changes had happened. She bit her lip a bit in concentration as she added another note of her own.

I'm trying to give you the benefit of the doubt. I suppose if you hadn't been through what I had, Memory Charming our parents wouldn't seem so bad if you had some good reason. But don't think I haven't noticed you haven't actually given me any demonstrably relevant reasons yet. Oh, and what good is not telling people about V or guarding my thoughts when Mr. Odious (thank you for that, I shall think of him as nothing else from now on) already knows and indeed has a written copy of some of them?

Hermione added three drops to slightly less than a half-glass of water this time, and waited. Sleep came more quickly this time, but slowly enough that she had time to marvel - a bit wearily - at how bizarre her life had become, even compared to a week ago, let alone three months.

o-o-o

After waking again and checking her watch, Hermione saw about twelve minutes had passed that time, and more writing had appeared. She swiftly read the new lines.

Thank you, I'll take what I can get.

I'm not sure how smart Mr. Odious is, and thus how likely it is that he's taken what we'd consider logical precautions against theft and/or Memory Charms, but it's probably not worth the risk. Considering his family, and his House, I'm afraid to say that what P suggested might actually be safest - find some counter-leverage on him and make it in his own interests to keep quiet about it. He might even admire you for it, if it's done well, not that I think you ought to be making friends with him, or any Slytherins for that matter.

Continuing on with the previous discussion - the H.R.C. (and T.T.) is not the only means of interacting with Time, it's just the only one even hypothetically predictable enough to be considered sane to use. What happened to me - and in turn you - is one of the other ones. And I admit I don't understand it at all - it involved some non-human magic, plus I think another thing the Department of Mysteries studies beyond Time. I am not an Unspeakable - I thought there were better uses for my time than research which by definition almost no one ever learns about or benefits from, although I admit I'm questioning that decision now even more than I used to. Though if I had gone down that road, I wouldn't have found myself in this situation anyway. I also don't understand how Erasure works. It doesn't seem to make logical sense, but a lot of magic doesn't, I'm afraid. It's admittedly possible the reports of Erasure were entirely fabricated by the Ministry in another effort to discourage the use of Time magic - it wouldn't be the most questionable thing they've ever done by far. But I will note that there have been a discouragingly large number of Dark wizards and witches throughout history, many of them quite obviously psychotic, and not a single one has been recorded to have meddled with Time, not even to prevent their enemies from being born or similarly obvious things. If someone like that thinks something is too dangerous to use, that really ought to say something, don't you think? In the end, the safest assumption seems to be, if you attempt to use Time in anything but the simplest and most predictable ways, it will not go well. I obviously can't prove it...but ask yourself, does the magical world look like it ought to if people were able to change Time safely?

Hermione didn't particularly approve of the remark about not making friends with Slytherins, though it was hard to argue in Mr. Odious' case. And she was surprised how much ignorance her older self was admitting with respect to non-standard Time magic. But even if it made her trust her honesty a bit more, it did not seem like a strong argument. There were too many unknowns. Besides which, even if you accepted something like the "perversity of Time", the details of how it even worked were unclear ...for example, Hermione wasn't from the future, wasn't trying to change her own past, it was all still ahead of her - couldn't that just as well mean anything she decided wouldn't apply in the same way? Or was everything "infected" by the initial disruption, whatever it had been, each event in turn, ad infinitum?

She jotted down her response.

That still doesn't seem good enough, there's too much uncertainty. And the fact that Time doesn't appear to be getting changed is almost entirely meaningless...if Time were changed properly, safely, you wouldn't expect to see anything at all. Yes, I suppose I might hope the world would look better than it does, but we don't know how it might've looked otherwise, maybe this is much better...plus, suppose Time is being used by multiple people with different opinions on what's ideal, couldn't you end up with some sort of consistent vectored average?

Would you please explain exactly how this whole thing happened to you, to the best of your knowledge? And in your notes, you mentioned someone else possibly having "come back too", T.D. - is this my partner from Defence? Won't she change too much even if I don't?

She took another dose and impatiently waited for sleep.

o-o-o

I see what you mean...the observable evidence could have a selection bias, because Time may affect what's actually observable? But I still think the risk is too great, since the scope of harm is effectively infinite.

And I'm sorry, but I'm not going to give you the details...given your arguments, I can't conscience the risk of you trying to replicate them. All I will say is that there was an accident involving an unfamiliar magical substance. Someone else was present at the very end who I think was that T.D., but I'm not certain, it all happened very quickly and I hadn't seen her for a few years - and regardless, I don't know that she was actually included, that was just speculation. And knowing myself, I'm sure that you could probably research it even without any other details, but I urge you not to. It was powerful, barely controlled magic, triggered in almost certainly the wrong way, and the odds of it going the same way twice are beyond astronomical. It's entirely possible it killed me, and I suspect it may have somehow done even worse damage on top of that - but I won't explain that either, so please don't bother asking.

In my opinion, Miss Davis shouldn't be relevant to your decision - even if a similar thing did happen to her, I've taken certain steps to minimize changes as a result. Steps which weren't options in your situation. Again, I apologize, I know this is going to frustrate you and not help our relationship, but it's not up for debate.

Hermione stared at the writing, frustrated almost to the point of saying a rude word. She'd sworn to herself that when she was older, she would never, ever treat someone like some adults - her parents included, on occasion - had treated her...as if her thoughts, her opinions, were of no conceivable value, because she was a child. And now here she was, doing it to herself. True, it wasn't quite the same...if anyone had the slightest chance of holding that position and it actually being accurate, it'd have be a future version of herself...but even so, it didn't feel good at all.

Her quill stabbed at the paper.

Wow. Nice to know I grow up to be a hypocrite. I hope whatever you convinced yourself was okay to do to Tracey wasn't unduly influenced by your opinions of Slytherins in general.

In any case, you still haven't convinced me. Of course, since I'm only a child, it wouldn't be surprising if I got all petulant and just stopped listening to you entirely, but I'll go ahead and try to set an example of reasonable behavior for you and let you keep trying anyway.

Hermione stirred more drops into another glass of water with such vehemence that she almost spilled it, and with her bristling thoughts, it took a good five minutes for her eyes to droop closed.

o-o-o

Hermione rubbed her eyes as she awoke - they felt puffy and bleary. She also actually felt a little sleepy still this time, and looked at her watch curiously. Over half an hour? It didn't look like that much extra writing had appeared on the paper. Maybe she'd just been giving it extra thought? At any rate, the nap seemed to have helped Hermione's irritation, and now she was just deeply weary, rather than angry. She was sure she could work herself back up if she wanted to, but she recognized that wasn't a helpful impulse, and she suppressed it, instead returning to reading the new notes.

Very well.

Given that what I've already said isn't enough, I do have a more consequentialist argument - specific to Madam Pomfrey, but indirectly applicable to everything else I'm sorry you're now burdened with. The situation with V is deadly serious. We managed to come through it with honestly a lot less loss than we had any right to expect. Certainly, we owe our success to skill, hard work, and sacrifice. But also a great deal of luck. The more things change from how I remember them, the more likely it seems some of that luck won't go our way. The person I strongly suspect is responsible for Madam Pomfrey is, and will be, responsible for other things - some very bad, but others which influenced other critical people in critical ways. Leaving him to continue much as he might have, with Madam Pomfrey on top of everything else...yes, it's horrible, there's no other word for it...but it's still the best I can think of, and in that case, he should receive his just desserts in the end.

I can imagine your counter to that, because I've considered it myself - all of the advance knowledge I have, in the hands of the right people now, ought to be able to make up for that uncertainty. Who needs luck when you can cheat? And if this were just a Prophecy, I might say yes...though there are dangers in relying on prophecy too - you really can end up causing what you're trying to prevent - but most prophecy seems to have some uncertainty "designed" in, and ignoring them would be foolish.

But this is where everything else comes back in. Relying on unknown Time magic, and the very strong possibility that because of it events will go in the opposite direction we want, even perversely so? We'd be responsible for all the consequences, and things could have gone much, much worse than I remember them - suffering for all of Britain, maybe the entire world, muggles included. Do you really think you can live with that on your conscience? I don't think I could, and I've had to do worse things than Memory Charms.

Even given your feelings on this sort of thing, if I could just safely wipe all of this from your mind and hope for the best, leave you as I "found" you, I probably would. But I can't. Besides, it's only barely more morally defensible than me just taking control completely, which I'm also not going to do, no matter what you decide. In the end, this is your life, not mine. I'm just trying to give you the best advice I can and hoping you make the correct decision...which may not be the logical thing for me to do, but feels like the right one.

I truly wish I could help more, but that's all I can tell you, really, and I sincerely hope it helps more than it feels like it has. Either way, I wish you the best of luck, and as happy a life as you can find.

The new section ended with her full name, signed with an elegant flourish. Hermione leaned back and set her head against the cool stone of the bathroom wall, closing her eyes.

This is really, really unfair, she thought, more plaintively than angrily. There should be a decision which was both right and best, but instead she seemed to have only two choices, equally uncertain and full of risk, not just because she wasn't allowed to have all the information that seemed necessary, but because some of the information simply didn't exist.

She could do what felt right to her, to help people now - in every way she knew about - and risk unconfirmed but legitimately terrifying temporal consequences. Or do nothing as, somehow, the Gryffindor version of her was advocating. And try to live with the secret, the regret, as bad things inevitably happened and she wondered if she might have prevented them. All in the hopes that Time would somehow of its own accord get back on track so, best-case, things "worked out" and only a few good people ended up dead, but which given the changes already, honestly didn't seem at all guaranteed either.

Hermione's heart sank as she suddenly realized why the decision was being left to her. What her other self had said about there not being a lot of time, not taking control completely, what the notes had said about her slipping. She was going to go away, to let herself "die", for lack of a better word. Which on the face of it appeared extremely ethical, brave...even noble, and was probably intended that way. It was what Hermione had thought about earlier, sacrificing herself to save someone else, but in a deliberate, premeditated way. It made her feel humbled, and guilty, since she still wasn't sure she could do the same thing, even if they were technically the same person. But in which case her older self wouldn't have to live with any of the long-term consequences either way, because she'd be gone, which meant ethically, it genuinely ought to be Hermione's decision.

But the other reason, that she'd grasped in the same moment, was the chilling suspicion that her older self, despite who-knew-how-much more education and experience, despite her seeming confidence in her opinions, knew there was no good decision in practical terms...if she had, despite the ethical issues, wouldn't it have been worth taking over permanently? Even if it effectively "killed" her younger self, to make certain things went as they should, if the stakes were as high as she believed? So, lacking enough justification for taking the responsibility herself, her older self was abdicating the whole thing to her, and in that light, the act didn't seem very noble at all.

The not-quite-twelve-year-old girl found her cheeks were wet again, but unlike at the memorial, this time she was almost certain she was crying for both of them.

o-o-o-o-o

A/N: I know, so gloomy! I promise this is just the darkness before accepting hero's call, and from here on out will be climbing upward, tooth and nail, slide rule and wand. ;)

Edit: Thanks to /u/rational_username for catching a doubled word!

And /u/nikic for the "Letters" that snuck in to Physical Review D, despite my explicit check. I blame Gregory Benford. ;)

Chapter 15: Responsible

A/N: Sorry about the delay, life got busy again. But I'm still plugging away, as determinedly (if not perhaps as diligently) as our heroine. :D

o-o-o-o-o

"I'm just saying, our first Astronomy class tonight is going tae be harder than it needed tae be, because someone was banging around the bathroom at all hours last night, sniffling like a house elf with a head cold!" Morag's unnecessarily loud complaint cut through the fog of sleep, and Hermione sat up in bed, rubbing her eyes blearily.

The morning sun was streaming through the room's open curtains, and her dorm-mates were moving about, mostly dressed already - though in casual outfits, since Friday was entirely free except for the recently mentioned Astronomy class at midnight. Morag, seeing she'd finally managed to wake Hermione, smiled tightly, and Hermione sighed.

"I tried to be quiet, I'm sorry I disturbed you, Morag," she mumbled. The disagreeable girl sniffed sharply, but didn't otherwise acknowledge the remark.

"Good morning, Hermione," Padma said quietly, stopping by Hermione's bed. "Are you okay?"

Hermione considered the question. Last night had been equal parts depressing and frustrating. And while her older self's arguments had been presented lucidly enough, in the light of the morning, they still didn't really seem to make sense.

She wondered if there might have been side-effects from whatever happened to send her older self's mind backwards through Time. Or possibly her own brain wasn't developed enough to 'emulate' O.H.'s full thought processes, so they were handicapped somehow? Or even while Hermione herself was sleeping, there still just wasn't quite enough 'spare' capacity? She'd have to ask Professor McGonagall exactly how one maintained consciousness after being Transfigured to a non-human form, or how ghosts managed to think at all. And then there was that bit her older self had included about possibly something worse than being killed having happened to her, whatever that meant. All of which only firmed Hermione's instincts to favor her own judgement in this case.

But then what? Given the school's sealing, she suspected at a minimum the Headmaster had evidence of - or at least suspected - foul play. But if he did, he was no doubt already looking for the killer, and Hermione's information was so vague that it might not actually be helpful...the most valuable piece seemed to be just knowing it was murder in the first place. Even if she came clean, since there was no way to prove her story, the Professors might just chalk it up to that infuriating Confundus misinformation. And if they did, there would be more unnecessary visits to Madam Wainscott, or they might even confine her "for her own good" since she wasn't ignoring her "delusions" as instructed, and then she wouldn't be able to help at all. From her reading, she knew the standards for involuntary commitment to St. Mungo's were higher than the equivalent in the muggle world - wizards in general seemed to have a much higher tolerance for what they deemed 'eccentricity' - but it did happen, and that seemed not yet worth the risk.

She could owl an anonymous letter to someone in the DMLE, but even if it were believed, she presumed it could cause a lot of problems for Hogwarts - and she still wasn't sure if the Headmaster and whoever else was involved in the cover-up had good reasons for their actions. Hermione decided to hold that option in reserve...besides, it would also be far more likely to succeed with some verifiable evidence. There was always that journalist, Ms. Skeeter, who seemed all too likely to accept Hermione's suspicions at face value even without evidence, but that too could cause problems...suppose there was a public outcry, the school was opened to outside investigators, and that was the thing that allowed the culprit to get away?

Then there was the issue of her older self's apparent intentions towards self-sacrifice. Objectively, if anyone would, she ought to know whether or not there was any other way. On the other hand, she'd admitted she didn't really understand what had happened, and if her logic was compromised for whatever reason, then could she really be considered responsible enough to make a decision like that, however much Hermione might ordinarily support someone's "right to die" from an ethical standpoint? Which meant on top of everything else, she felt obligated to try to find a way to rescue her, or at least help her make an unencumbered decision about it.

"Hermione?" asked Padma, looking concerned, and Hermione realized she'd just been sitting there staring and hadn't answered the girl's question.

"Sorry. I'm just...tired..." she said softly. Despite her quiet tone, Morag's eyes glittered from across the room.

"Aren't we all," she snipped, moving to the stairs. "Well, I'm going to breakfast, coming?" Mandy and Su, looking uncomfortable, moved to join her. "Padma?" prompted Morag when the other girl hesitated.

"I can wait," she offered to Hermione. Hermione shook her head.

"No, go ahead. I'm...not really hungry anyway..." Padma looked as if she wanted to say something, but just nodded, and followed Morag and the rest of the girls downstairs.

For a minute, Hermione just sat there and considered going back to sleep, but as daunting as her problems were, avoiding them wasn't the answer. She slid out of bed, then fumbled open the jar of chocolate-covered espresso beans, popping a couple into her mouth and chewing mechanically as she headed to the bathroom.

As she'd expected, by the time she'd cleaned up, brushed her teeth and put on some casual clothing, there was no chance she'd get to the Great Hall before breakfast was over. Instead, she just headed directly to the library.

o-o-o

Checking the school rolls had been a bust - there was no male student with the initials P.P. enrolled this year. Which implied that the murderer had been masquerading as a different student, or hiding in some other way. But after another hour of frustrating research - trying to find books with useful information in the perversely inefficient library - it turned out there were a lot of ways to conceal or disguise one's self with magic, most of which weren't visibly obvious even if you knew what you were looking for.

Disillusionment or an invisibility cloak did often leave subtle visible disturbances. Reviewing her memory of the train ride, she didn't think she'd seen any, but then it's hard to say if she would've noticed, particularly if she'd been moving herself at the time. It appeared that a Confundus Charm could convince you a person was someone else, though that seemed impractical, since you'd have to repeat it every time a new person saw you, and then what, Memory Charm everyone else who saw you casting the Confundus?

Whereas Polyjuice Potion, Self-Transfiguration and Metamorphosis were entirely dependent on individual skill - even a Metamorphmagus could be considered "skilled", since it was an inborn talent but required practice to develop - and could be effectively perfect, unless you knew the person being impersonated well and could spot inconsistent behaviour. But Hermione hadn't known anyone well, and the killer didn't even have to be masquerading as a specific student, they might've just looked like a student in general. On reading the description of a Metamorphmagus' abilities, it seemed clear that's what Tonks' "trick" was. She might've been the killer playing a double-game, pretending to be someone pretending to be someone else...but Hermione wasn't sure what the point of that would've been above simply pretending to be someone innocuous, which made her think Tonks was probably just what she'd seemed - a helpful but bizarre recent Hogwarts graduate.

Then there was the other magical disguise, an Animagus transformation. That seemed almost not worth considering, since the process was apparently so difficult and dangerous that it was extremely rare. The Ministry actually required people who'd managed it to register, and there had been only seven in the past century - including Professor McGonagall, which certainly spoke to her dedication to leaving no aspect of Transfiguration unexplored. Though, the reason the Ministry required registration was the somewhat odd presumption that people would otherwise be tempted to use an Animagus form for criminal activity - as if magic in general wasn't otherwise overburdened with opportunities for wrongdoing?

That bothered her, so Hermione dug deeper, and discovered that an Animagus form was not detectable by any broad spell...the only way you could be sure was if you attempted to reverse the transformation, and that was itself a difficult spell, or compared the results of an inconveniently long series of Charms while the person was transformed. And since there were Charms that could otherwise duplicate most of the benefits you'd get from being one animal or another, it meant that you needed a really good reason to specifically attempt the Animagus process instead. It also meant that until someone was actually caught in the act you'd never know, so there could indeed be a much larger number of Animagi running around out there than the registry implied. Though again, probably not many, given how difficult it was.

None of this really helped her much. On the train, taking into account her efforts to help Neville, she'd encountered dozens of students and their pets, any one of which might've been the disguised killer. And while Trevor's repeated escape attempts were a little suspicious now that she thought about it, there was nothing that linked the toad to Madam Pomfrey, unless he'd taken ill and Hermione just hadn't-

Taken ill. Diseased.

Hermione clutched at the library table as the blood dropped out of her head so fast, her vision swam and she swayed dangerously. Nurse Wainscott had said that the Headmaster and all the Professors agreed there weren't any people in the hospital wing when the nurse had left Madam Pomfrey alone, nor had anyone entered before the nurse returned.

But there had been a rat.

Because he'd bitten Malfoy's friend - and been yellow at the time - Scabbers had been taken to the hospital wing to be checked to make sure the bite might not have passed anything along. Hermione had even thought at first that he'd been killed by the same vapor that claimed Madam Pomfrey, and been so relieved when she'd learned he wasn't that she hadn't questioned it. But why would Madam Pomfrey return the rat herself rather than have Ron come fetch him? And she would've presumably done any number of diagnostic Charms...maybe even the ones that would have revealed an Animagus. And if he, in desperation, took his human form to silence the witness to his disguise, would that count as "entering"?

But...that doesn't make any sense… Hermione rationalized, a bit desperately. Ron said he'd been passed down from his brother. Sneaking into Hogwarts once is one thing, but why would someone live as a rat for years? But hadn't one of the Twins also said that their father had arranged an exception for Scabbers 'ages ago'? She was almost certain she'd read that the lifespan of a natural rat was almost never longer than three years.

Her fingers whitened on the edge of the table.

Hermione had, years ago, accidentally left a shop with a book without paying for it - she'd been with her parents and had used her bookbag as a shopping basket, but when the time had come to make their purchases, she'd missed pulling one out to be rung up. When she eventually discovered the mistake at home, she'd been wracked with panic and guilt, and had considered all sorts of insane plans to cover up the "crime", including walking five miles back to the shop in the middle of the night to sneak it back in (somehow), or burying the book in the backyard (even then, destroying it had never occurred to her). Eventually, after a sleepless night, responsibility had won out and in the morning at breakfast she'd tearfully confessed to her parents. She was a bit taken aback that they only wanted to pay for the book - they seemed to think she had punished herself sufficiently via her own guilt. But even if she hadn't done it deliberately, it was wrong.

Hermione had intellectually understood that some change to Time had resulted in Madam Pomfrey's death, and the source of that knowledge implied that it was probably something she'd been involved in somehow. But it was just an abstract part of the insane situation she'd found herself in, and she hadn't really dwelled upon it. But, now, upon realizing that - despite her immediate attempts to cast doubt on the conclusion - she had a plausible explanation of how her direct actions had gotten a person killed...the impact was devastating, and Hermione's mind nearly came apart at the seams.

Moving slowly and haltingly, Hermione swept her things into her bag and stumbled away from the table, out of the library. She might have vomited, but fortunately there wasn't anything left in her stomach to seek escape. She was barely thinking, let alone navigating, and it was only upon seeing the impressive ugliness of the gargoyle that she broke through the fog and realized where her legs had been taking her.

"Headmaster's office," she murmured, recognizing the guarded entrance from Engineering Enigmas. It was, all things considered, long past time to talk to a responsible adult, and let someone else tell her what the right thing to do was. But the problems were the same - would he believe her, enough to investigate? Without taking the Time business into account, her suspicions were extremely circumstantial...and if she did bring that up, either he wouldn't believe that either, or he would, and then there'd be no going back, no hedging, she'd have to reveal everything.

Despite the sympathy she'd felt last night, Hermione hated her older self a little bit for putting her in this position. Though she did notice that there was no attempt to stop her, no sense of sourceless panic - she really was on her own.

"I need to speak to the Headmaster," she said, her voice shaking, to the revolting gargoyle. The book had noted the entrance to the Headmaster's Office was protected by a passphrase, but Hermione had no way to know what it might be.

Nothing happened.

She tried again, this time with a hand against the stone statue, then her wand, but again nothing. Feeling frustrated, and a bit silly, she knocked on the stone, and received only mildly abraded knuckles for her efforts.

"Honestly, there must be some way for him to receive unscheduled visitors…" she mused, rubbing her sore knuckles absently. Her voice was more steady this time, as her irritation beginning to mask her nervousness and guilt. Then again, he was very busy, perhaps he was out. Or appointments had to be scheduled with the Deputy Headmistress?

Despite herself, the obstacle was giving Hermione an opening to second-guess her decisions. She could always come back later...and every second she delayed was another second the murderer might find some escape, or commit some other awful crime. Even if she went to another Professor, that still applied, and who knew how long it would take to convince them?

More and more, it felt like the genuinely responsible thing to do would be to get Scabbers securely captive first...then there'd be less chance of anything happening due to a delay, plus he'd be right there when she revealed her suspicions, and thus a lot harder for a Professor to refuse to check...

Hermione slowly walked away, leaving the motionless gargoyle behind, and began to seriously consider how a first-year witch might subdue a murderous adult Animagus, even if he was a rat the vast majority of the time.

The notion that it might not be possible did occur to her, but she dismissed it - she'd just have to be creative.

Chapter 17: Gang Aft A-gley

"All right," said Hermione, pausing outside a disused classroom. "Before we get go to the hospital wing, I think we should test my theory. If you'll give me Scabbers, I will turn around, then one of you - don't tell me who, and don't say anything - go in the classroom and pick two corners of the room randomly, walk to each, then come back. When you're done, I'll go in with Scabbers and test the spell - if he can tell which corners you went to, and lead me back to the right one of you, then we're in good shape." The Gryffindor boys stared at her in confusion.

"But...why don't we just test it in the actual place, save some time and trouble?" asked Ron. Hermione shook her head.

"If it turns out not to be practical, there's no point in even trying it and risking getting in trouble with Madam Wainscott or anyone else. Also, this way we can check the answer, because you two will know it, whereas in the hospital wing, we couldn't be sure it wasn't just a guess or something?" Also, I needed to prep the room first, and that would've required an additional pretense to get Madam Wainscott out, Hermione added, silently. The boys looked at each other.

"Makes sense to me," said Harry. Ron shrugged, and handed over the rat - Hermione steeled herself carefully to avoid showing her revulsion, though again wondered if it might've been more in character for her to be uneasy about handling a rat.

She also made a point of standing so that she couldn't see what the boys were doing, but angled slightly so that the rat - if he were so inclined - could in fact spy on them. Better to give him every opportunity to cheat now, to feel as smug and confident as possible in whatever he decided to do.

There were quiet noises behind her as the boys exchanged gestures to work out who would go in, followed by the sound of the door opening and closing, then doing so again after a brief delay. At the second door closing, Hermione turned back to face Ron and Harry.

"Ok, just wait here. It might take a little while, since I'm going to be very careful, so please be patient? Oh, here," she added as if it was an afterthought, pulling a quill and a scrap of paper out of her bag and handing them to Harry, "once I've gone in, write down which of you went inside, and which corners you went to - it's important in science to document everything as you're doing it." Harry nodded, though he glanced at Ron, which probably meant Ron had gone into the room, but then the blind nature of the experiment wasn't actually the point, after all. That taken care of, Hermione entered the room and closed the door behind her.

"Can I really trust them to wait, though?" Hermione asked herself quietly, deliberately forcing uncertainty into her voice - though this was not all that hard, considering. She withdrew her wand from her bag and aimed it at the door. "Colloportus," she said, making a tied-knot gesture with the wand tip. Throughout this process, she did not yet put Scabbers down. An Animagus transformation - indeed Transfiguration in general - conserved the location of the center of mass unless the accommodation of the process otherwise shifted it. But she obviously couldn't support the weight of an adult man with one hand, which meant if he reverted now, he'd probably end up falling at least 30 centimetres or so to the floor, and Hermione was hoping he'd wait rather than risk turning an ankle or something. Either her guess was accurate, or his plans didn't suit changing yet, because the rat remained quiescent during this process.

When making her preparations, Hermione had picked the room partially due to its proximity to the Gryffindor common room, but also because it was a fully interior room and did not have any windows. She'd also carefully checked along the base of the walls around the room's perimeter for any chinks or holes a rat might squeeze through, and found none - thus the door was the only way in or out. She knew that if things went horribly wrong and the murderer somehow escaped what she'd planned - and had a wand - her simple Locking Charm wouldn't hold, but it would slow him at least a moment. While turning away from the door, she surreptitiously kicked what appeared to be an oddly-shaped collection of wood fragments about three inches high - it skittered on the stone floor and ended up roughly centered on the doorway.

The classroom only held a handful of desks and no table, so her path to the center of the room was largely unobstructed. Hermione glanced around, making sure everything was in place, took a breath to steady herself, then started Step 4. She couldn't help tensing as she set the rat down on the floor - this was his first good chance to try something - but for the moment he seemed content to play his part as she was playing hers.

"I'll have to go over the spell a few more times," she said, "I'm sure Ron won't mind if you have some biscuits while you're waiting…" She removed a pair of Bourbon creams from her bag, setting them down before the rat, then reached back in for Practical Household Magic, all the time not letting go of her wand. Ostensibly this was to review the Supersensory Charm, but in actuality it was just a prop for a brief delay. Hermione watched carefully over the top edge of the book to see if the rat seemed at all suspicious, but he had begun devouring the chocolate-flavoured biscuits without hesitation.

In a little more than two minutes, he'd finished eating and cleaning his face and paws, and seeing Hermione still apparently muttering over her book, settled down patiently to nap. She waited as long as she dared, but if she waited too long most of her planning would end up wasted, and plus the longer she waited the more tense she became - she wasn't sure she'd have the nerve to go through with it. Hermione took a few more breaths that she'd intended to be calming, but had little effect on her churning stomach. Her hand shook a little as she tipped her wand down past the edge of the book, but she held her breath, waited for it to steady...waited…

"Emméno," she said, with a double-flick of her wand, aiming the (non-Permanent) Sticking Charm at the rat's left forepaw, currently resting against the stone floor, his other paw crossed over it and his head atop both.

At once, the rat awoke, and - as she'd hoped - instinctively planted its other paws for leverage to try to free the first. Hermione immediately cast another Sticking Charm at the other forepaw, then each of wthe two rear paws for good measure, ignoring the rat's increasingly frantic squeaking. Hermione put the book back into her bag and kept her wand trained on her captive.

"You needn't bother - without a wand in hand, I'm pretty sure you couldn't get loose from even one of those, let alone four. Also, I know you're not a natural rat, and that you murdered Madam Pomfrey, probably because she discovered that too." Hermione tried to deliver this declaration in a tone of quiet confidence, but she found by the end her voice was a bit shaky. Her wand, at least, stayed steady enough, if not quite as steady as the proverbial rock. As for the rat, he had frozen, looking up at her by the start of the second sentence. By the end...the rat's form had begun shifting, growing. Hermione readied herself just in case it turned out her tests hadn't been rigorous enough, or the results couldn't be extended to an Animagus transformation...

But they had, and could, and she relaxed - slightly. The rat had become an adult man. It was hard to tell in his current posture, but it seemed like he was on the short side, balding, in casual robes that had deteriorated to the point that they were little more than rags. Even if he was short for an adult, he was decidedly rounded, and probably outweighed Hermione by at least a factor of three. His slightly beady eyes rolled wildly, his face a mixture of outrage and fear - but much more of the latter.

As Hermione had tested, with the help of a few Engorgement and Shrinking Charms, a Sticking Charm retained its enchantment even under shifts in size, and thus his entire palms were still affixed quite firmly to the stone floor, rather than tiny rat-paw-sized patches of them. His shoes were not - Hermione supposed because whatever kept his clothing suspended in the transformation didn't apply to the accommodation of the Sticking Charm, so the charms on his feet had dissipated being otherwise separated from the floor - or perhaps were simply holding his shoes on? And though the centers of the charms on his hands had shifted, each area had to continue to overlap the original area defined by the spell, so his hands were now touching, thumb-to-thumb. Unable to support himself in that position, he'd toppled forward, his legs splaying out, elbows bent awkwardly to avoid putting uncomfortable pressure on his wrists. He looked up at Hermione in a panic, eyes wild.

"No, no, no...you have it all wrong! I'm a marked man, I'm hunted, I had to hide...but I didn't kill the Healer, I didn't!" Hermione wasn't inclined to simply take his word for it, but he did seem truly terrified.

"You were there...the staff checked, and no one else could've done it," she pointed out, reaching into her bag with one hand while the other kept her wand on him. The man shook his head frantically.

"The staff checked...was Snape one of them?" Hermione frowned, and the man's expression became desperately triumphant. "He's always been one for lying and sneaking and secrets...I saw him kill Pomfrey with my own eyes...I only just managed to open that cage and escape before he set up that subterfuge with the salamander blood and the quills, protected by a Bubble-Head Charm the whole time! When the other staff investigated, he must've interfered...subtly, carefully...and covered his tracks!"

While Hermione tried to wrap her head around this accusation, another part of her automatically continued the plan, since either way, there was no good reason not to. She did not direct her wand away from her prisoner, but instead brought her other hand around in front of it just long enough for her Finite to catch the tiny object she held, which - no longer under the influence of seven stacked Shrinking Charms - agreeably ballooned outward until it was the normal-sized magical camera she'd borrowed from Penelope Clearwater. As much as she would have liked to quip 'Watch the birdie…' or something, surprise was paramount in the Plan as she didn't want him to have any chance to transform back into a rat at this point. So while the man was still trying to grasp what he was seeing, she centered him in the viewfinder and poked the shutter button with the tip of her wand. He blinked and sputtered from the large flash, looking even more desperate if anything. Hermione set down the camera carefully, keeping her eyes and wand on him.

"What motive could Professor Snape possibly have for killing Madam Pomfrey?" Hermione asked, though there was not as much skepticism in her voice as there might have been. She now rather regretted not having had Harry explain precisely what he believed about the Potions Professor. Before the man could respond, a loud pounding began on the door, and muffled voices. Hermione simply sighed, while her prisoner startled violently, wincing at the pain this produced in his hands.

"Oh, Merlin, who's that?!" he cried. Hermione shook her head.

"That is the sound of someone who - presumably because they are Gryffindors, or possibly because they are boys - upon hearing a Reminder Charm on a quill tell them there is an emergency and to find whoever of Professors McGonagall, Flitwick, Quirrell or Dumbledore is nearest and bring them here as fast as they can, rather than doing that, have instead elected to shout and also pound pointlessly on the door that I prudently took the precaution of sealing. Though the latter was mostly for you," she added dryly. "Professor Snape?" she prompted, after a moment. The man blinked.

"He's a secret Death Eater, has been for years! Pomfrey must have suspected something about me after all those tests she did, and he somehow learned of it first - I'm marked, I tell you, I was in the Order of the Phoenix, fought against the Dark Lord...Snape came to do unspeakable things to me, but first he had to eliminate the witness…" Hermione stared. That was ridiculous, Professor Snape was...well, a Professor. Teachers didn't go around being evil and murdering people, they just didn't. And if you were secretly evil, why on Earth would you go around deliberately trying to look evil? Professor Snape, like anyone, probably had various problems, but being stupid didn't appear to be one of them. And yet, Harry had learned something… Hermione glanced at the door, but by now the pounding had stopped. Looking back, she found the man had also noticed, and his panic had increased.

"Do you have any evidence of that, other than your claim that he killed Madam Pomfrey? And if you knew he was evil, why didn't you just tell Dumbledore earlier? You've been living with the Weaselys - as a rat - for years!"

"I...didn't have evidence! If I'd accused him, Snape would've wiggled out of it somehow, and then some odorless, tasteless potion would've found its way into my soup, and I'd have tragically choked to death or something!"

"So just tell Professor Dumbledore what you told me, surely-"

"Snape's muddied the waters, I told you! Unless...you could let me go, let me be a rat again, use your Charm, and I'm sure I can find Snape's trail. But even with him in Azkaban, the Dark Lord still has other secret supporters, I'd never be safe...just don't tell anyone, let me live as a rat, please, I'm fine with it, I'm a good rat…" Hermione's confidence was wavering, but her sense of propriety just couldn't let this last one go.

"Look, you can't just carry on sleeping in children's beds as a rat, it's just...you just can't, okay?" She shuddered. "And besides, I, ah, don't actually think the Supersensory Charm will work that way...that was a sort of trap. Just wait, the Headmaster is a really amazing wizard, I'm sure he can think of a way to keep you safe…" The man, who'd been staring at her throughout, began to thrash, his face twisted in frustration and terror, eyes rolling wildly, wincing each time he strained to free his hands - one of which, Hermione noted, was missing a finger. Suddenly he slumped into a sort of dejected squat, his chin falling to his chest. "I'm really sorry," Hermione said, feeling a lot less good about the whole thing than she'd expected to, "I can't release you, but if you're telling the truth, everything will work out...somehow…"

Could Snape have actually done it? Hermione still didn't know what spells the staff had used to investigate, maybe they could be fooled, particularly if you knew in advance what spells were likely to be tried, and were actually present there to make certain. But could he have done it right under the Headmaster's nose? Then again, while Professor Dumbledore - at minimum - had been sharp enough to suspect foul play, he hadn't managed to find Scabbers or Professor Snape, so maybe he wasn't infallible. And that bit about muddying the waters wasn't hard to imagine, given how easily her future self had done it to her. But something else had occurred to her.

"If you were just running for your life, why did you steal Lavender's wand? And, more importantly, why run back to Ron's room, if you say Professor Snape knew who you were, wouldn't he just-" Hermione's question was interrupted by a terrible cry of mingled exertion and pain as the man lunged upwards from his squat with desperate strength. His scream mixed with a nightmarishly wet sound as all the skin from both of his palms tore free, gory handprints left behind on the stone. He staggered back a step, off balance from the sudden lack of resistance, his face contorted in pain.

Hermione had tried to think of ways the Plan could go wrong at each stage. She'd moved all the furniture away from the center of the room (and put some of it to other use, besides) so he couldn't reach anything with his feet, or with a free hand in the event she'd only been able to get one stuck before he transformed. But this hadn't occurred to her at all, and even though she still had contingencies that might help, she simply wasn't emotionally prepared for the sight of a man mutilating himself to get free of spells she'd cast. And she wasn't even sure he was guilty anymore, he might just be so terrified he'd lost his reason. She froze in indecision.

One of his bloody hands reached into his tattered robes and pulled out Lavender's wand, face twisting as he tightened his flayed hand around it, pointed it at her. A part of her noted that this still didn't prove anything, but the rest of her decided it still looked pretty bad, and her hesitation broke.

"Expelliarmus!" she cried, giving her wand the appropriate diagonal flick. But the man slashed his wand downward, causing a bright flash as her spell was parried. He aimed his wand back at her, but Hermione had planned this sequence in advance and was already dropping onto her stomach, her own wand extended. His wordless spell finished first, but sailed over her and struck the wall behind. But he was still fast and experienced, and was able to sweep his wand down in another parry as Hermione shouted, "Illubrico!"

However, the strategy she'd worked out had called for her to - just in case he already had a Shield up - aim this spell at the floor, and since the Lubricating Charm did not form a visible projectile, he was unable to adjust his parry to block the spell's unexpected trajectory. The stone became nearly frictionless, and the man's feet shot out from under him, dropping him heavily onto his back.

At this point, Hermione hesitated - she was encouraged that her spell combination was actually working, but the next part called for her to manually trigger a fail-safe that ought to disable him. Except during her planning, she'd presumed that if things reached this point she would be in a life-or-death struggle and basically anything would be justified - including the fail-safe, which might cause serious injury or even death - whereas now she was uncertain enough to question that. But her instincts said she had no choice - and as long as he wasn't killed outright, if he was innocent, Madam Wainscott and the Professors ought to be able to set everything right.

But the brief hesitation to weigh the moral considerations had been costly, and even as she began to point her wand upward, her opponent had recovered from his fall and launched his own spell. Hermione tried to dodge, but she was too slow, and before she even got two syllables out, her wand was sailing out of her hand to clatter into a corner of the room. I should've thought of that, tied a safety strap to it or something, but I was expecting Curses, not a Disarming Charm, maybe he really isn't a horrible murderer after-

"Crucio!" snarled the man, struggling to his feet. Blood spattered the stone beneath him, scattered drips from his free hand mixing with staccato spurts between the fingers of the other, squeezed out by the pressure of his grip on the wand.

Thought vanished as Hermione's world became pain. It was like her blood was on fire, or like her blood had been Transfigured to hydrofluoric acid, or something even more gruesome, except she couldn't really form these concepts, only feel them - there was no room for anything but the searing, hateful agony. And then it was suddenly gone, leaving her twitching and panting on the stone floor - blood no longer burning, but muscles still aching from their involuntary contractions, her cheeks wet with tears, one of her fingernails chipped from clawing at the hard surface beneath her.

"Tell me what you know about me, what you've told!" screeched the man. "Tell me, so I can fix it…" Murderer or not, he was clearly unhinged at this point, and Hermione was terrified - she was pretty sure she'd do anything not to feel that pain again. But she still only answered the second part of his mad demands.

"Y-you...were there...only w-what I...told Ron and Harry," she stammered out, between gasping sobs.

"Who else?! You didn't plan this trap yourself, who is helping you?!"

Hermione's mind cast about frantically for what he might want to hear. She wondered if he'd believe her if she told the whole truth...maybe that'd be enough time for a Professor to actually get here, since it seemed like the man's own heart-pounding fear - and maybe the pain in his hands - was interfering with what was supposed to have been her second fail-safe. And the Cruciatus Curse hadn't triggered the first...maybe that was why it could eventually drive a victim insane, you never lost consciousness from its effects, no matter how much you might want to? He raised the wand again, and Hermione's train of thought vanished as she immediately began to speak as fast as she could form the words, her brain barely connected to her mouth.

"No one, honestly, I tried to talk to Dumbledore but I couldn't get into his office or he was out and I asked the Defence Professor for advice but it was all hypothetical and they all think I've been hexed so I needed real proof which is why I borrowed the camera, but the trap I just thought about and I've always been quite good at thinking, but now I'm rather suspecting I'm not smart at all and maybe I should have been in Gryffindor, because I can't imagine how I expected for a second any of this would-"

"Dissocio," he interrupted, swishing Lavender's wand downward into a alternating flick at the end. Hermione gasped - recognizing a Disassembly Spell, and suddenly horrified at the thought of what it might do to a human body - but the spell was not aimed at her. Instead the camera turned into an exploded diagram of itself, all its individual parts separating and hanging in the air for a moment, then dropping gently to the floor. "Accio proof," he continued, waving the wand vaguely at the scattering of camera parts, and the film agreeably soared towards his free hand, but he recognized the problem with this and an additional flick sent the roll to the floor in front of him before it could contact his bloody, fleshless palm. Another flick and the mottled appearance of the exposed film changed to a uniform brown-black. A final swirling motion sent the film and all the camera parts back together, each fitting neatly into its proper place.

While the man was carefully destroying her evidence, Hermione shakily stood up. Her wand was several yards away, and the only other ways of deliberately triggering her fail-safe she could think of seemed both unwise and unreliable. Though if it appeared he was about to use the Cruciatus on her again, she thought she might just go ahead and try one anyway. In the interim, she tried edging towards her wand as subtly as she could. She'd only made it about halfway when his attention turned back to her, whereupon she froze and tried to give the impression she was terrified into abject submission - a feat which did not require much acting ability, under the circumstances.

"Accio wand," he said, aiming his own wand to the side, but keeping his eyes on her. Hermione's wand obediently leaped into the air and landed neatly in his free hand. He grunted at the pain this caused, but maintained his grip on it. "Trying to be clever? With me? I can always see what people want to hide..." The little man gave a hollow laugh, and Hermione couldn't keep disappointment from touching her features. He tucked Lavender's wand into his robes, and switched Hermione's to his right hand.

"What...what are you going to do now?" she asked, her curiosity only barely edging out her fear at hearing the answer.

"No time to stage a convincing death scene for you, it'll have to be a Memory Charm," he mused.

"So you did do it. But...if you can do Memory Charms, why did you kill Madam Pomfrey in the first place?" Hermione asked, aghast.

"I'm not very good at them," he said, with a shrug and an elaborate yawn. Hermione's heart briefly swelled with hope, but even if the Liquid Sheep she'd dosed the biscuits with was finally starting to kick in, it was taking forever...the dose must've been diluted within his greater body mass. But if he kept talking long enough… "I don't know enough Potions to pass off that kind of mental damage as an accident. But with that convenient Hex as an excuse, I can probably get you shipped off to St. Mungo's permanently, convinced of something ridiculous - say, that Grindelwald had escaped and had for some reason transfigured himself into a desk somewhere in Hogwarts…later, when I've had enough time to work something out and suspicion to die down, I can arrange a tragic accident for you too. " He raised her wand.

"Wait!" interrupted Hermione, desperately. "If you're going to Obliviate me anyway, can you explain why you were really hiding as a rat first?"

"What would the point in that be?"

"I'm a Ravenclaw. If I have a choice between not-knowing and knowing...even temporarily...I'll choose knowing." For a moment, it looked as if he actually empathized with her, but the rat-faced man shook his head.

"I recognize stalling when I see it, and reinforcements could arrive any minute."

Hermione dove to one side as he opened his mouth again. She didn't have much hope of actually dodging the spell he was about to cast, so she also flung her arms backwards, piking forward, trying to hit the stone floor headfirst as hard as she could manage and if she was very lucky, triggering the other fail-safe before-

"Petrificus Totalus!" The spell might have helped her, preventing an instinctive flinch, except that it also forced her rail-straight, so the impact was distributed more evenly across her entire body instead of just her forehead as she'd intended. It still hurt when her nose hit the floor, but not as much as the realization that she hadn't planned carefully enough, she hadn't read enough...she was going to be Obliviated again, probably be committed, and then - at some point - die.

It wasn't supposed to have been like this. Probably all kinds of people thought something like that in their final moments of clarity before some ignominious end, but Hermione suspected she was unique in actually having fairly strong evidence on which to base that assertion. If this was how Time really worked, this disproportionate ruination of everything, she didn't think much of how the Universe was arranged. It was petty and nonsensical and frankly, someone ought to put Time in its place.

She really hoped someone would, even if it obviously wasn't going to be her.

"Obliviate."

There was a terrible wrenching disorientation.

Chapter 18: Struggle

Hermione found herself lost in chaos. It was like when she'd fallen into her older self's memories, in the Library, except this time it was Hogwarts' history she was seeing. But only fragments, in no sensible order, some things mixed together. She saw the school run by a Blood Purist Headmistress. She saw students die. She saw the Founders, blending their incomprehensibly strong magic into to the magic of the land itself, to give the castle a kind of permanence and life that no later structure would match. She saw Triwizard Tournaments (and more students die, incidentally). She saw Salazar Slytherin and Godric Gryffindor in such a row that the veins stood out in their necks, but they never touched their wands.

It all became a jumble, one thing running into another with no pattern, too fast to follow, and just as Hermione began to fear for her sanity, it faded, withdrew. She could feel, somehow, that it was still happening somewhere inside her, and realized she was being shielded from the Memory Charm - at least for the moment - but at a terrible cost. Worse, her instinctive interpretation of the sensations suggested desperation and weakness.

Hermione spared no time on grief for the other her, and simply felt grateful, while she frantically searched for some way out of this mess. But while she was still paralyzed, unless she somehow deduced how to produce wandless, motionless magic in the next couple of minutes, it seemed like this was only delaying the inevitable. Maybe if she was wrong about her protection being temporary, he would finish his spell, thinking it was successful, but allowing her to act freely?

Then her nose, pressed against the stone floor, twitched. As the rest of her body gradually followed in returning to her control, Hermione controlled her shock and tried to keep herself as rigid as she'd been before - she wasn't sure how much spare attention a Memory Charm left the caster, but she could not afford to let the murderer notice something was awry.

Hermione began to think even faster, mystified as to what hat her older self had pulled this rabbit from, her heart racing apace with her brain. She could move now, and that was a significant improvement, but her options were nevertheless rather limited.

She could just wait and hope that the sleeping potion would slow or disable him, or Ron or Harry would show up with a Professor before the Memory Charm fought its way through, but that was a pure gamble. Banking on his Memory Charm finishing before it chewed through her other self and reached her own mind was a similar bet on unknown odds. She could try to run for the door, but it was still sealed, and without her wand, she had no way to open it. She could try, again, to knock herself unconscious to trigger her fail-safe, but Hermione doubted she had the strength to do so from a prone position.

Hermione closed her eyes, picturing her last view of the scene before she'd dived to the floor, examining every detail she'd seen. Her surroundings, cleared of anything useful save her own impotent "fail-safes", the murderer, looming before her, a wand gripped in each hand, blood dripping from the man's flayed palms-

A rather Gryffindorish idea occurred to her at that point, but she made note of it, set it aside, and continued to consider the situation carefully. The floor was still lubricated from her spell, which meant he was either standing very carefully, or, more likely, had moved away from his previous position, which meant in turn that her fail-safe was probably entirely useless at the moment - a rather significant hole in her original preparations, she now realized. But there could still be some of the lubricant on his shoes from contact, as well as the blood randomly dripping from his hands. She could try to tackle him, and hope the treacherous footing would aid her, but despite his stature, he still outweighed her and was probably stronger as well.

Suppose she just stood up, blank faced and glassy-eyed...was it plausible that a Memory Charm might allow something akin to sleepwalking, or interfere with a Full Body-Bind? Maybe the FBB was a mental block, and not an actual physical force. Even if that wasn't the case, he'd admitted he wasn't very good with Memory Charms, and he'd fallen for the Supersensory Charm notion...maybe he wouldn't know for sure - possibly be thrown enough to delay, to investigate? But he had seen through her edging towards her wand, and seemed much better at intuiting intent than she was - now that he wasn't as overconfident - certainly better than she was at deceiving in the first place. He probably wouldn't let her just shuffle within reach of him in any case.

And yet...his obvious pride in learning what other people wanted to hide, his seeming empathy when she'd begged him to explain, just so she could know. What if he thought he'd lose something by continuing the charm...something he'd never get back...

As the seconds ticked down with no further insights, Hermione grew a bit desperate. Carefully choosing a course of action from all the available options was all well and good, but there were such things as time constraints, and sometimes you were just forced to work with what you had. An unlikely feat of agility and dexterity - neither of which were strengths, though she had been working on dexterity at least - or a far-fetched deception to lure him into making a mistake. She could feel the Memory Charm nearly touching her, and she made an instinctive decision.

Hermione dutifully rehearsed the plan, imagining likely slips, making corrections. When she felt a grey fog creeping in at the edges of her vision, she knew she could wait no longer.

"...Memory...for the best...never know...secret…" she murmured into the floor, but loudly enough that - assuming he could hear at all - he couldn't miss it. She tensed, ready to try the other plan if it seemed he hadn't heard through his concentration, or was otherwise not taking the bait. But immediately, she felt - somehow - the Memory Charm slow, then pause, but not stop. There were bare tatters of her other self's protection left, nothing that could be called thought. The best metaphor Hermione could come up with, from a source as mysterious as the sensation itself, was as if a book had been dropped, page-by-page, into a diamond-cut document shredder, then a tablespoon of what remained was sprinkled into a spiderweb.

Two quick footsteps - and a noise that suggested he'd nearly slipped but recovered himself - then she felt a hand roughly turning her over onto her back. She kept herself mostly but not entirely stiff, leaving room for some awareness - beyond her having spoken at all - that she wasn't fully frozen...he mustn't be too startled when she did move, lest he jerk away in surprise. But she did try to keep her face slack, her eyes dull and half-open.

"What? What secret?" he demanded. Hermione could see now that he'd put one of the wands away, and held only one - hers - in his right hand. But she forced herself to keep her eyes unfocused, not even to glance at it.

"...you...don't know…" she murmured, more quietly, airily raising her right hand to point at him. His eyes widened in confusion and he leaned in closer.

"What secret, what don't I know?!"

Hermione smoothly extended her reach, grasped her wand, and pulled as hard as she could. As she'd hoped, the blood on his palms had not congealed, but was still flowing from the horrible damage he'd done to them. It acted as a lubricant, and despite her disadvantage in relative strength - though his missing index finger no doubt helped there - her wand slid free of his grip, eliciting a hiss of pain. Her sense of the suspended Memory Charm vanished instantly.

"You're even worse at Memory Charms than you thought!" Hermione shouted into his face. She couldn't cast with the wand reversed, or holding it like an ice-pick, so as she shouted, she twirled it in her hand like a baton - thanking her juggling exercises. But even as she closed her fingers back around the wand in a proper grip, the man overcame his pain and surprise and reached out to wrest it back from her.

With no time or room to cast, she flung her arm to the side to keep it from his reach, and though his shoes slid and he half-fell, it was mostly onto her, pinning her wrist against the stone. When she tried to take the wand out of her right hand with her left, he seized her left wrist - her skin crawling as his flayed hand wrapped around it - and wrenched it to the other side of her body, pinning it just as he had her right.

Hermione kicked at his legs and body, but their respective positions didn't allow her to do much more than annoy him, and - no doubt by design - she couldn't bend her wrist enough in this position to point her wand at any part of him. But lying on her back, past his furious, half-panicked expression, she saw something she could target. She bent her wrist as far as she could manage, aiming the wand at the ceiling in the center of the room. Silently thanking Professor Quirrell for the extra bit of practice, she jerked it upwards as sharply as she could, giving it the proper back-and-forth half twist, and hoping the tiny distance she was able to thrust it with her wrist pinned was sufficient.

"FINITE INCANTATEM!" she roared. The murderer's face was contemptuous, though shaded with a hint of confusion. He began shaking her wrist and slamming it against the floor, trying to dislodge her wand, but Hermione hung onto it doggedly - her spell, if it had been successful, was already cast, but it was a distraction at best and she couldn't afford to lose her wand.

During her preparations - what seemed like years ago - Hermione had selected the classroom's heavy worktable as the best candidate for her failsafe. She'd discovered that - after multiple Shrinking Charms - the formerly very sturdy and thick oak legs could be removed by a succession of Severing Charms that would've been useless against them otherwise. After she'd removed them all, Hermione had managed to charm the table's surface to nearly the exact color of the ceiling, then lodge it there amongst the vaulting with the strongest Floating Charm she'd been able to cast after multiple attempts - and positioned precisely over the spot on which she'd planned to stick Scabbers to the floor.

The thick slab of oak - which Hermione had estimated weighed at least 50 kg - now restored by her Finite to its original color, size, and mass, and freed as well of the magic which had been maintaining its vertical position a good fifteen feet up, dropped to the floor about two yards behind them with a tremendous crash.

The murderer, in a panic, released her in order to scramble away, looking around wildly for the source of the noise even as he fumbled in his robes for Lavender's wand.

Hermione didn't waste time by trying to get to her own feet, she just swung her own wand over to track him, aiming across the length of her body.

"Petrificus Totalus!" He'd managed to get Lavender's wand out, but not fast enough to parry. The spell, however, failed to contact him as he instead used his Animagus transformation to dodge, his form shrinking rapidly down to that of a rat again.

Now Hermione leaped to her feet, and sent spell after spell towards the rat, starting with more Full Body-Binds but switching to Rictusempra which was slightly quicker to cast, then Engorgement Charms, which were faster still and might make him easier to hit subsequently, and finally - steeling herself - Severing Charms, which were the fastest yet. But the rat was too small and quick, and she couldn't land anything. Even after she tossed in another Lubricating Charm - which affected a sizeable patch when cast at the floor - given the benefit of claws it barely affected his speed at all, though he did seem to have slightly less manoeuvrability.

But despite all her efforts, she saw he was aiming for - and likely going to reach - some of the desks she'd moved to the back wall of the classroom. Hermione realized that if he managed to shift back to human shape behind them, he'd both have some cover and be able to parry spells, while she would benefit from neither. She turned her back and sprinted for the door, wand extended before her.

"Stupefy!" she heard in the distance behind her, at the same instant she cast her own spell. Not at the door, but the small irregular pile of wood fragments she'd taken care to center just past the doorway as she'd entered.

"Finite Incantatem!" she yelled, leaping upward and forward. Despite her attempt to avoid it, her feet were caught slightly by the rapid expansion of the tangled pile of chairs and desks she'd repeatedly Reducio'd into manageability, causing her to tip forward in her jump and crash into the door heavily. But the pile itself blocked the Stunning Spell, and she was encouraged to find herself still awake and alive. The pile had been meant originally as a contingency - another wildly optimistic one, she now realized - against blocking pursuit if she had been forced to flee. Cover hadn't even occurred to her...not having ever been in an actual spell duel, her analysis of likely outcomes and tactics had been woefully incomplete.

Hermione wanted to take a moment to catch her breath and shake the fog out of her thoughts that had come from hitting the door nearly headfirst, but from the other end of the room she heard an incantation she did not recognize, followed by two she did, but which taken together were all extremely alarming and highly motivating.

"Bombarda Maxima! Stupefy! Avada Kedavra!"

Hermione recalled, at some point in the past week, idly wondering what the propagation speed of targeted spells was, and further, if it varied. In broad terms, it was clear that they were generally fast enough that simply dodging wasn't easy, but not so fast that parrying or dodging physically wasn't possible. She had, at the time, been in the middle of something else and hadn't interrupted it to jot the question down on her list. Now the question was of significantly more than academic interest, as the classroom was long, but not that long.

Hermione, in a time-saving instinct inspired by pure terror, tried an Unlocking Charm, which was both two syllables shorter than the General Counter-Curse, and - if properly cast - would cause the sealed item in question to physically open as well without requiring additional effort on her part.

"Alohomora!" she cried, twitching her wand in a quick double-flick upward and leaning away from the door to give it room to move. As soon as it had opened just wide enough she dove forward. But Hermione had scarcely made it halfway through when she was flung upwards and tossed towards the opposing corridor wall as her makeshift barricade - along with most of the door as well as some of the stone floor and doorway itself - exploded with shocking violence.

"Aaahhh-Arresto Mo-" she started, trying to convert her scream into something more useful, but even if she'd had the focus to cast under the circumstances, there was simply not enough time over the short distance across the corridor, and her incantation was cut short as she was slammed brutally against the stone wall, then battered and scoured by fragments of debris as she dropped heavily to the floor. The scattered contents of her bag joined her, loose sheets of paper fluttering everywhere, some covered in notes, others blank - some of the latter having been liberated from her copy of Hogwarts, a History, whose oddly worn binding it seemed had finally given out completely.

Hermione hurt everywhere, she felt dizzy and nauseated, and she seemed to be having trouble hearing, both in general and from a persistent ringing. Accordingly, she mostly saw, rather than heard, the impact of two searing magical bolts slam in quick succession into the wall above her, the blazing red a metre or so up, while the sinister green only missed her by centimetres. It also felt like something warm was trickling through her hair, and she suspected this was very bad without devoting too much of her very limited focus to it. She had somehow, in a small miracle, maintained her grip on her wand.

Through the dust filling the air in the corridor and the otherwise-open doorway, Hermione could see the rough outline of the murderer approaching from the far end of the room. She could not make out his expression, but she imagined it was grimly satisfied, though still a bit worried, because this would be pretty hard to cover up, and the noise presumably meant people would now be rushing here from every direction. Really his best bet at this point would be to make certain she was dead, transform and lie low, and then show up later and hope no one would suspect the rat. The shape of his silhouette suggested he was raising his wand, but he hadn't cast yet - he probably couldn't quite make her out, lying as she was against the wall and surrounded by dust and debris. But as soon as he was close enough to see that he'd missed, and be more sure of his aim...

It seemed like she should do something about that, and a very tired part of her thought just playing dead would be a fine idea, but Hermione rejected this as more groundless optimism. If she were evil, she'd certainly make sure her enemy was dead. Though when she tried raise her wand arm to do something, she nearly fainted from the sharp stab of pain. It hadn't really registered in the general chorus of her body's many complaints until she moved it - some part of her wondered curiously if that's what a broken bone felt like. Her arm was already pointing in roughly the right direction, however, and conveniently she'd just had a little practice in casting with only her wrist. She tried to keep her arm as still as possible and though it still hurt quite a bit managed to the complete the wand motions for a Full Body-Bind this time, but when she took a deeper breath to speak the incantation, she felt another stab, now in her chest, and despite herself released what little air she'd claimed in a croaking cry. The man must've heard, because the speed with which his shape through the dust was growing closer seemed to increase, and very faintly, mostly by the rhythm, she managed to make out "Expelliarmus", repeated several times without pause.

This seemed manifestly unfair, so Hermione, in an impulse born as much from petulance as tactics, simply opened her fingers and let the wand fall to the stone floor. Or she would have, except now the murderer's blood on the wand was congealing and it had adhered relatively well to her palm. She felt a tingle as one of the wildly-aimed spells struck her, but the wand remained. Sticking didn't count as holding? She began to laugh, but the stabbing pain in her chest stopped her quickly. Hermione instead stuck her tongue out, thinking of Hannah Abbott roughly a million years ago at the Sorting, and vaguely wondered if she was thinking clearly, but dismissed the question as not something she was equipped to address right now. Yet through the fog and distraction, she did remember that she was meant to be doing something, and though it sent another stab of agony up her arm, she closed her fingers back around the wand and stubbornly tried the gestures once more.

Whether it was the fact that she was now bracing herself for it - and had suffered the Cruciatus Curse not long ago and had somewhat recalibrated her scale for what agony meant - or perhaps simply that she was going into shock and beginning to lose feeling entirely, this time she was able to maintain her focus through the pain, and to draw just enough breath.

"Petrificus Totalus," she whispered, and the way her hearing was, she couldn't really tell if she'd even managed to speak aloud. Maybe the murderer couldn't either, or his reactions were dulled by the cumulative contest of the Liquid Sheep versus his adrenaline, but he didn't begin a parry until - to Hermione's mild surprise - a blue-white flash of light burst from her wand.

But by then, at their current distance, it was too late. His limbs snapped into alignment with his body and he toppled forward through the doorway, his eyes full of disbelief.

The surge of relief washed away what little adrenaline Hermione had left. Her vision went dark, and the world fell away.

o-o-o

Hermione stared up at a cloudless blue sky. She was outside? But she'd been in the castle...doing...something… Feeling something smooth and slightly cool under her hand, she bent her neck forward and saw she was wearing a simple but lovely blue silk dress, her slippered feet peeking from under the hem. Part of the curve of the Black Lake was visible beyond...also, she seemed to be lying on a table. She turned her head to the right, away from the lake, then immediately sat up and swung her legs off of the table, trying to make sense of what she was seeing, though it was uncomfortably familiar. Facing her were rows upon rows of chairs, though not very many were filled. All of the Ravenclaws in her year were there, plus Roger Davies and Penelope Clearwater, the older girl fussing over her camera. Ron and Harry sat together, and the Weasley Twins, plus Hannah and Lavender were nearby. The latter was whispering to Parvati, next to her, but she was glancing unhappily at Neville, who was focused on clutching Trevor tightly in his lap. Tracey Davis was tugging on Theodore Nott's sleeve, trying to tell him something, but he was ignoring her. All her Professors were also there, plus the girl from the train, Tonks, along with the Headmaster, and...her parents.

Almost everyone looked very sad, though only her parents were openly crying.

A strange fear gripped her, as she suddenly remembered the last thing she'd been doing, her desperate duel with the murderer, her serious injuries. Not that the fear was unreasonable - it was actually a fairly universal one - but it was strange because despite having met a few ghosts, she still hadn't really adjusted her otherwise entirely scientific opinions on life-after-death, and had thus not anticipated having the opportunity to experience this particular fear post hoc, as it were. She slid quickly off the table.

"It's okay, everyone, I'm all-...ah, I'm still here…" she said, correcting herself when she remembered that ghosts were a possibility now, and thus 'all right' might not be wholly accurate. But no one seemed to notice at all. They were still looking in her direction, but they weren't looking at her. Feeling a chill, she slowly turned around to look at the table.

The girl lying there barely looked like her. True, she was only slightly more pale than her usual skin tone, but there was the lovely dress, her styled hair. Her hands were folded neatly atop a pristine copy of Hogwarts, a History which lay on her stomach. She was perfectly still.

Hermione swayed and might have fallen, but strong hands were there to steady her.

"Headmaster?" she gasped, looking up into Dumbledore's face. "You can see me?" He gave her a sad, kind smile.

"I see everything. I'm a powerful wizard, haven't you read my Chocolate Frog card?"

"But...am I a ghost? No one else can see me…and you can touch me…" He hastily removed his hands.

"You must've been mistaken, that would be extremely inappropriate, particularly at your funeral. Anyway, I have a duty here, so if you'll excuse me?" Hermione nodded mutely, extremely confused, as Dumbledore moved to a podium to one side of the table. The audience grew quiet.

"We are here," he said, in sombre tones, "to say goodbye to Hermione Jean Granger. An otherwise gifted girl who, entirely due to her own mistakes - whether they occurred in this timeline or not - died without quite having reached the age of twelve. Which would no doubt be very disappointing to her, were she around to think about it...I mean, honestly, within a matter of months everyone here will have done better, even Ronald Weasley and Neville Longbottom, who are each blessed with unique character deficits we all sincerely hope they will work on."

Hermione stared at him, then thought back to the Welcome Feast and wondered if Madam Pomfrey's memorial had just been an unusually lucid moment. But looking out at the audience, no one seemed to find anything he'd said unusual or surprising, not even insulting Ron and Neville, or mentioning timelines. The Weasley Twins had moved behind Professor Quirrell, and were beginning to carefully add pizza dough and cheese to the garlic already in the folds of his turban, which seemed both dreadfully inappropriate and unwise, but certainly not impossible...

"She did manage, sort of, to defeat a rat in magical combat, though that is only slightly more impressive than it sounds, considering. She could have just told me about it, but despite being Sorted into Ravenclaw, she was completely unable to figure out how to get into my office while I was taking a short nap, even though the password was 'password'. She didn't even guess," he added, shaking his head sadly. "Mr. Potter could've done better, and he's a muggle-raised orphan, and nearsighted to boot." Much of the audience nodded as if the Headmaster was dispensing great wisdom, Harry included.

Morag suddenly stood up.

"Yes, Miss McDonald's, tee-emm" asked Dumbledore politely, making finger-parentheses around the '™' as he pronounced it.

"Och, ah just wanted tae say," she began, and seemed to now be wearing a tam o' shanter and a kilt, despite being a girl, "e'en thoo sh' deid aft'r her first week and ah'm obviously goin' tae get way mair Hoose Points than her, ah ken fair certs ah certainly could've dun better e'en if she hadn't kipped it." She sat down, to polite applause.

"Quite right, Miss Macaroni, and well said. Even though I did already point out we'd all do better than her in the not-dying department, and I couldn't really follow whatever language you were speaking, I think we got the gist."

"I'm sorry, I mean...what? What? So, yes, the dress is very nice and I'm glad someone did something with my hair, but this is a horrible funeral..." objected Hermione, who had finally managed to find her voice. "There aren't even any quotes from famous authors, or soothing music on oboes, it's just rude and bizarre…" Dumbledore put a finger to his lips and shushed her, and Hannah stuck her tongue out in her direction, the Twins interrupting their surreptitious construction of a scale-model bistro around Quirrell's head long enough to follow suit.

"In any case, I know we all have better things to do, so let's just get on with it." He withdrew a wand from his robes - black and smooth, with a white tip - indistinguishable from a standard stage magician's wand by virtue of being one. "Abracadabra!" The body on the table was consumed by intense white flames, which quickly vanished, leaving only the book. It fell to the table's surface with a soft thump. The Headmaster waited for a moment to see if anything else was going to happen, then shrugged. "Weird. All right, off with you then. Madam Pince will be along to collect the remains at some point, if she isn't too busy being unhelpful at Library patrons."

Everyone got up and dispersed, chatting amiably with each other. Hermione tried to follow, still objecting that this whole thing was in terribly poor taste, but she couldn't seem to move further than a few steps away from the table.

She wondered if she might contrive to carve a wand out of one of the table legs, but lacking a wand in the first place or indeed tools of any kind somewhat stymied that line of thought. She was interrupted when Madam Pince did in fact walk down from the castle to the table, but after she picked up the book she swerved towards Hermione herself.

"Books left out of the Library! Shame! Shame and disrespect!" She opened a book bag that looked a lot like Hermione's, dropped the book in, then grabbed the hem of Hermione's dress and began feeding it into the bag as well.

"Wait, I'm not a book!" Hermione heard herself shout, rather unnecessarily, and wondered if Dumbledore's insanity was catching, even posthumously. But the librarian ignored her, and in a few moments had somehow stuffed Hermione herself entirely through the bag's opening, which had improbably widened enough to admit her.

o-o-o

It was a horrible mess in the bag, which, from the inside, looked somewhat like a circus tent. Her notes were scattered everywhere, but they were effectively the size of large sheets of plywood, and just as difficult to lug around. And while her wand was here, it was similarly unwieldy, looking more like an unusually ornate utility pole than a delicate magical instrument.

Hermione fanned out most of the pages across the bottom of the bag with great difficulty, but they were hard to sort when she couldn't properly look at more than one or two letters at a time. She used the enormous thread and thimble from her emergency sewing kit along with a ballpoint pen cap to make a pulley system, then laboriously tipped a spiral notebook up onto its edge and used the wire binding to climb up towards the top of the bag and look down. This was even more difficult than it sounded, because her dress had at some point become a pinafore and her petticoats were getting in the way.

"So, top-right, then second two rows down, then fourth one up from the bottom," she muttered to herself, figuring out the proper order. She was only halfway done when the bag lurched and she slipped, beginning to tumble head-over-heels towards the rather unyielding book cover below.

"Oh, bother," she said. "Arresto Momentum?" Despite her hesitant intonation and the fact that her wand was some distance away, her fall downwards stopped instantly, though it immediately restarted, because of course the Earth's gravitational field was entirely functional inside the book bag, and momentum and acceleration were two entirely different things. "Arresto Gravitate," she tried instead.

This time her fall did not stop, but she stopped accelerating, and floated relatively gently down with the same speed she'd had when she spoke. She nodded approvingly that magic was finally starting to make sense even if nothing else did at the moment, though when she reached the book's cover, she simply bounced off of it and headed straight back up, lacking any gravity to otherwise hold her. Hermione saw a bright light above her and realized she was going to sail straight up out of the bag entirely - she looked down and waved goodbye to her notes, and they each wiggled a corner at her.

o-o-o

Hermione looked around curiously. She seemed to be in the Hogwarts Library, but if so, someone had radically redecorated since the last time she was here. The architectural features, the stacks, the books - everything was in its proper place and configuration, but it was all white. Bright white. Madam Pince wasn't anywhere in sight - no one was, come to think of it - but perhaps she'd simply chased Professor Flitwick out after he had, for some reason, tried out his room-coloring charm again.

"Hello?" she called out, experimentally.

There was no response, but there was a change. She could now hear the soft, comforting sound of pages being turned, about once every twenty seconds or so. For the average non-fiction book, it was a pace a bit rapid for nearly anyone who wasn't skimming, but the rhythm was as familiar to Hermione as her own heartbeat. She searched through the stacks, pausing occasionally to listen, until she located the source of the sound.

A young woman - perhaps Nurse Wainscott's age - sat in an overstuffed chair in one of the many little alcoves of the Library. Her legs were tucked under her, and her clothes were modern muggle standard, except as white as everything else - she noted her own clothes were now her Hogwarts robes, though equally white. Hermione recognized the book she was reading at the same time as the woman herself.

The woman looked up, gave her a welcoming smile, and patted the arm of the similarly-overstuffed chair adjacent to her own.

"It's all right, really," she said, quietly. "It's not what you think...so to speak." This should not have been reassuring, but somehow it was anyway, at least enough to break Hermione's hesitation. She moved to the empty chair, toed off her shoes - she noted there was a mirrored pair in front of the woman's chair - and climbed up, curling her legs under herself similarly, but sitting turned, to face the woman over the arms of the chairs.

"I'm not sure what I think, but...I'm not dead, then? I mean physically - obviously I'm not last-year's concept of dead, or I wouldn't be asking, cogito ergo sum and all that." The woman smiled again.

"Neither. If you'd been discorporated, I think you'd know it...whatever ghosts are, they don't seem to have the capacity for..." she paused and waved a hand airily, "...this sort of thing. Given that, the other follows - you must have a living brain with which to indulge in whimsy. At least for the moment." Hermione frowned.

"Are you sure it's not you indulging in the whimsy? You seem awfully pleased with yourself, whereas I'm just confused. Case in point, I thought for sure you'd been wiped out by that Memory Charm…" The young woman shrugged.

"I'm pretty sure 'I' was." As Hermione's frown deepened, she continued, "And before you offer any objections about that contradicting the implications of what I just said, let me clarify - I am exactly as sure as you are that whatever constituted 'me' was in fact irrecoverably destroyed." It took Hermione a moment to parse this.

"Oh. You're saying this is all coming from me, and you're not really 'her'? Goodness, that makes a lot more sense now...I didn't want to believe Dumbledore was that crazy…" She paused. "But if this is all a dream, is there a point? Beyond the usual, at any rate." Another shrug.

"I'd say it's an open question as to whether she was 'really' her in the first place. You'd have to look into the question of continuity of consciousness across Transfiguration and other radical alterations to physical instantiation, and that's a thorny puzzle indeed, since from your reading, you already suspect magical society doesn't seem to understand consciousness any better than science does. As for your question...what's the point of anything? It's a little nihilistic, but I'm serious. You learn, you grow. Ostensibly so you can survive long enough to pass your genes along to some offspring and give them a decent chance at doing the same. In this particular case, along the way, brains have evolved ways of trying to right themselves when they've taken a particularly hard knock - physically or otherwise." Hermione considered this.

"What, so I may be dying? And I have to choose whether to go on living or not? That's a bit clichéd...but anyway, you know my answer to that, so I guess we can just skip to the end?" The woman laughed, but it didn't sound kind. The light through the windows began to darken.

"Such a snippy little witch...so be it. And asking me questions about the future, little girl? I already know how this really ends for you, and it's not happy." Her form shifted and shrunk, but rather than turning into a rat, she turned into a mirror of Hermione herself, though still in white casual clothing. "You don't get to choose anything...you've already been trapped by the person you're staring at."

"I don't understand…do you mean the other me? Or...because it was really my fault Madam Pomfrey died?" The girl made a disgusted noise.

"You can be a bit thick sometimes, you know? But by all means, let's talk about that. You realized your actions had led to Madam Pomfrey's death. And because you felt guilty, you decided you could be as efficient as possible by punishing someone else along with yourself, and nearly getting yourself killed!" The girl turned and lifted her shirt halfway, showing a mass of bruises and cuts, half her ribcage sickeningly misshapen, one rib protruding here, a shard of wood piercing her there.

Hermione stared in horror.

"It's...but...you said it wasn't what I thought..."

"You thought you might be dead, and you're not. Yet. But that does not make everything okay." There was blood trickling down the girl's neck from the back of her skull, spreading crimson across her white shirt.

"I know I made mistakes, I'm sorry…" she protested, weakly.

"That's not good enough!" roared the girl. "Guilt is a useful emotion only when it helps you avoid making mistakes - not as motivation to recklessness! And casting a stupid Color-changing Charm wasn't even a mistake! You had no way of knowing what would happen...all the real mistakes came after!" Her face was pale, her cheeks hollow, her eyes dark, and Hermione found she was leaning as far away from her as she could while staying in the chair.

"I...I wasn't...the me from the future said…"

"Wah, wah, I had a visitor from the future in my head, nothing's my fault," she mocked. Hermione slid out of the chair and took a couple of shaking steps away from her.

"What do you want from me?!" The girl's expression became calculating for a moment, then furious again.

"I want you to be good for something. You have all these talents, but I haven't seen anything but a pretentious, selfish child, skipping about among whatever shiny things catch her attention for a moment. In all your plans for justice and transference, did you consider for a moment how your parents would've felt if you'd died in this act of sheer idiocy?!"

She hadn't.

Not even a little bit.

Not even really at her 'funeral', though she'd been rather distracted by trying to figure out all the strange behaviour. A part of her tried to object that when she'd decided to trap the murderer on her own, she hadn't been thinking clearly, it was a unique situation, but a growing opposition in her shouted it down. She'd abused her marvelous intelligence and rationalized herself into nearly throwing her life away, and likely ruining her parents' as well. Her splendid memory helpfully summoned up the image of her parents in the front row, clutching each other, wracked with grief.

Hermione collapsed to the floor, sobbing, while the dark shape of the girl moved close. The windows had gone totally dark now, casting the Library in gloom, and her form was a smoky mass, outlined only by scattered highlights from glistening blood.

"I lied, you know. Before?" it whispered, and the words sounded cold. Hermione looked up, uncomprehending. "You are dying, but oh so slowly...you're in a coma. You're never going to wake up, but you won't die, witches are long-lived, and I'll have an eternity to bury you in your failures. You're going to suffer, you'll wish you were in Azkaban..."

Hermione's thoughts flailed about without direction. This wasn't her subconscious, she couldn't hate herself this much, could she? But what, then? The murderer had been using a Memory Charm, not just to remove, but to add...how did that even work? What if it added your own thought patterns to someone else's mind, and they stayed there? Or could it be the Cruciatus? There had been plenty of references to the Unforgivable Curse in her reading, but precious few details about how it worked. Maybe there was always permanent damage, maybe children were more susceptible, maybe every time it hit you it broke something.

But the thoughts were frantic, none pausing quite long enough to be seriously considered, just a whirl of terror as the dark figure drifted closer and Hermione scrabbled backwards on her elbows along the floor, trying to maintain the distance between them.

"Please stop, please, I'm sorry, pleasepleasepleaseplease-"

"Stop?" shrieked the girl incredulously. She threw back her head and cackled, then leaned in, her face centimetres from Hermione's. "Round and round the carousel goes, the sights may change but everyone knows, it never stops it never slows, a stream of Fate that ever flows…" Her mouth was a manic grin, and her eyes were clock-faces, tiny hands spinning against each other.

"Time!" Hermione shouted, desperately answering the implied riddle, but simply knowing the answer didn't magically fix anything - it never had. The girl gripped her by the shoulders, and where she touched a grey coldness appeared and spread. "No! I didn't do it, it wasn't me, it was her!" Hermione protested, finding it hard to speak.

"She is you and you are she, and though you march on differently, all what has been will come to be, for threads may wander in the weave, but only tem-po-ra-ri-ly…" she continued, in a maddening chirpy sing-song. The - whatever she was, girl wasn't a meaningful label anymore...wraith? - laughed maniacally.

Hermione found herself slowly standing up against her own volition. She could vaguely see the grey had spread across her entire body, but she couldn't turn her head to look - instead she moved to a shelf and withdrew a book. Her motions were natural, not mechanical, but she couldn't change them, all she could do was watch, as she sat down to read while the wraith capered about her in crazed delight.

She couldn't even see the words, the Library was so dark now, but her body continued turning the pages, once every twenty seconds, and no matter how natural and comforting the rhythm had seemed before, it felt like a hammer nailing shut her coffin.

Hermione screamed soundlessly, trapped in her own body, then started running through incantations, though it was no more helpful than the scream - even if she'd somehow done wandless magic earlier, this felt somehow more real than that, and she wasn't even truly speaking.

Alohomora, Finite Incantatem, Optundo Pulvinus…

The wraith was moving about the Library, running her hands over everything. Grey spread in clouds from every touch, like milk into tea. Hermione didn't know anything to fix this, but magic didn't have to make sense, and she clung to the litany as if it were a life preserver.

...Wingardium Leviosa, Lumos, Colovaria….

She started to hear the thoughts of her grey Time-locked self, banal internal comments on the book Hermione couldn't even see, but it didn't matter because she'd already read it, and when those thoughts grew loud enough she was sure she'd be buried beneath them and she'd be lost.

...Tenere Altum, Praereptor Classicum, Echo Moratus…

The wraith was at the window, just enough in Hermione's view to reveal that her back was missing, she was hollow on the inside, literally papier-mâché, but glued with something dark and awful. Her arms were raised and the Library began to lighten somewhat as the grey spread out the windows, to the school grounds, even to the sky, but it wasn't a lightness that really illuminated, it was a lack of color, a lack of freedom, a lack of meaning. Hermione was being crushed by despair, she couldn't think anymore, but stubbornly continued, giving over to her subconscious to provide whatever it would.

...Nati Sopo Álla...Iláp Iak Nuozíhcra...Aro Nit Onórehtfele...

The wraith, in the midst of chaining the whole world in grey, suddenly whipped her head around, clock-eyes wide, and swooped towards Hermione, screeching in fury.

o-o-o

Hermione stared up at a cloudless blue sky. She was outside? But she'd been in the castle...doing...something… Feeling something smooth and slightly cool under her hand, she bent her neck forward and saw she was wearing a simple but lovely blue silk dress, her slippered feet peeking from under the hem. Part of the curve of the Black Lake was visible-

Wait, what?

She sat up abruptly and leaped off the table. She was back at the funeral, as were all the attendants, but they were grey, ghostly. Hermione rechecked her own appearance, and she seemed to be fine - for the current working definition of 'fine', at any rate.

She walked over to her parents, but didn't dare to touch them. It was all she could do to look at them. She leaned close.

"I'm sorry," she whispered. "If I get the chance, I'll try to...do better."

Hermione glanced back at her body on the table, clutching the book. This might be a dream, but it was her dream, and seemed to have an internal logic. Maybe if she left now, before the Headmaster 'cast' his 'spell'...

She tried it, and lo and behold, it worked. She hurried into the castle, which grew more and more white as she approached the Library. By the time she stepped through the doors, it was as bright as it had been, and she noted that again her dress had shifted into similarly white Hogwarts robes.

Again, Madam Pince was not here, but when Hermione checked behind her desk, her own book bag was. She reclaimed it, and withdrew her wand. It was stained with the murderer's blood, but there wasn't much she could do about that - you couldn't really point a wand at itself.

Hermione didn't say anything this time, simply navigated the same path through the white Library to the pair of chairs, where the woman sat reading. She stopped several paces away.

"What...what are you?" Hermione asked, her voice unsteady. The woman didn't deign to respond, and Hermione tried again. "What kind of game is this?"

"It's not a game," said the woman after a moment, not bothering to look up. "Nor is it real - you're dreaming, even if you insist on behaving otherwise. But it's nevertheless how things are." There was, perhaps, a hint of dissatisfaction in her tone, but mostly it held apathy.

"That's…not okay. I can't accept that." She shuddered. The woman shrugged indifferently.

"The Universe doesn't change based on your acceptance, or lack thereof," she noted, dryly.

"No...it changes based on our actions." Now the woman looked up, her eyes normal - the precise shade of Hermione's - but skeptical. "There has to be something I can do?"

"There doesn't."

"You're lying. I'll...I'll fight you anyway." The woman set her book down on the arm of her chair and shook her head.

"You wouldn't be fighting me. You wouldn't even be fighting yourself. You'd be fighting the Universe. Not just futile, but...in the entirely wrong context of action. It would be like challenging the Pythagorean Theorem to a fistfight."

"That's not fair," complained Hermione. The woman laughed, and it wasn't cruel, but was now faintly tinged with despair, which cut almost worse.

"The Universe doesn't really care about fairness, though it sometimes likes to pretend." She paused, and her look became considering. "Suppose, for the sake of argument, there were something you could do. What would it look like?"

Hermione looked around the Library. Even against the slight glare of the ubiquitous white, she could see hints of grey, underneath everything, subtly chaining the world together, just waiting to bubble up and wash over the surface. Her expression became worried, but then softened - slowly - into wary thoughtfulness that mirrored the woman's.

"It would look different." This seemed like a truism, but it also seemed to capture the essence of her commitment. She trusted the woman would know what she meant.

There was an eternal moment of pause while they stared at each other, and Hermione felt like she was balancing on a needle's point.

The woman shrugged.

"By all means, try." Hermione's sense of tension vanished. She slumped in relief, then looked around, frowning.

Another moment went by, less eternal, but more awkward.

"Er." Hermione said. "How do I…" The woman sighed heavily and picked up the book to begin reading where she'd left off. She shook her head and spoke without lifting her eyes from the pages.

"You're a Ravenclaw now...I suppose you'll have to work it out."

Chapter 18.1: Interlude - Quod Sequitur

"Blimey, we've already told you lot everything we know. For the last time - Hermione said she thought Madam Pomfrey had been murdered, and she thought she knew how to catch who did it, using Scabbers and a Supersensory Charm and 'Deeanay', but she wanted to test it first in an old classroom. Then a quill she'd given us started going on in her voice about if we were hearing this there was an emergency and we should go find the closest Professor and bring them back straight away. Naturally we tried to see what was going on in the classroom, but the door wouldn't budge, so we ran off looking, but everyone was already on their way to dinner so it took ages, and by the time we finally caught up to Professor McGonagall, convinced her, and got back, Dumbledore had already been there and it was all over!

"Professor McGonagall gave us the third degree afterward, but she wouldn't say anything, and they won't let anyone see her in the hospital wing. But Nurse Wainscott is being fierce rather than sad, so she must be alive - whereas Scabbers is still missing, dead for all I know." Ron scowled irritably and took an unnecessarily vigorous bite of potatoes. Throughout his friend's recitation, Harry had nodded along in confirmation.

"If we'd only been faster somehow, we might've...I don't know, helped," added Harry, looking pained.

"You're cracked, mate," opined Fred, cheerfully. George nodded.

"We couldn't get into the room, but we did get past the seal they put on that section of corridor," the other Twin added, lowering his voice conspiratorially. "Whatever happened there, it broke Hogwarts - have you any idea how hard that is? You're probably lucky you were nowhere near it."

"I heard a rumor from...someone...that she made some amazing secret Transfiguration discovery," gushed Lavender, whose mood had improved markedly just after arriving for dinner, when Professor McGonagall had unexpectedly pulled her aside, returned her wand, and gently admonished her to keep a closer eye on it. "And supposedly Professor McGonagall was still trying to decide if it was safe...she probably tried to use it to do some sort of forbidden Muggle Deeanay thing and it exploded in her face!"

o-o-o

"Yes, but that's stupid. What really happened?" demanded Kevin. Most of the other Ravenclaws at the first-year end of the table seemed similarly skeptical, though Morag appeared to be keeping an open mind about Hermione being a safety hazard.

"Well, it's Lavender," noted Padma, not exactly disagreeing. "But I could tell Roger Davies knew something, so I asked him point-blank," she continued, in hushed tones. "He denied it at first, but eventually he gave in and admitted that he'd managed to sneak past the wards they put up around where it happened. He said there were signs it was some kind of spell duel - his theory is that Hermione was right about Madam Pomfrey being murdered, but whoever was responsible found out she was on his trail and ambushed her before she could find him, and she dueled him. They haven't confined us to our dorms though, so either he got away completely - which he couldn't, because the castle was still sealed - or she won."

"Oh, Merlin save me," interjected Morag, "if ye want tae worship someone, go tae the chapel, Patil. I'll grant Granger might have some tricks, but it's obvious Dumbledore did the fighting, if there was any tae be done. Now can we just eat in peace?"

o-o-o

"I will not," hissed Pansy. "Don't you see? Pomfrey and Granger are both mudbloods - the Chamber of Secrets must have been opened!" Draco opened his mouth to deliver some withering insult, but thought of a better idea and said something else entirely, his voice low but pitched to carry.

"Hold your tongue, Parkinson. If one suspected the Heir of Slytherin had come to Hogwarts this year - and I'm not saying I have any knowledge of such a thing - and had opened the Chamber of Secrets...but had not announced himself openly, tell me, what does the true student of Salazar's house do?" He paused a beat for her expression to become trapped between stupidity and affront, then continued before she could retort. "He pays attention, and he waits - quietly - to see if the Heir requests his aid."

Draco let himself show a quietly satisfied smile as Pansy scowled and some of the others around him began to look at him appraisingly. He wished he did know who'd apparently almost blown up the increasingly annoying mudblood, but other people thinking it might have been him was nearly as good. Plus, while he doubted the Heir was actually here - for starters, he wasn't sure Pomfrey had been a mudblood, he couldn't see how the Board of Governors would have allowed her to win the position if she had been - if he (or she, he allowed, reluctantly) was here, Draco's little speech should have made it clear he'd be happy to join forces, and also wasn't a complete idiot, unlike most.

Theodore Nott said nothing. Malfoy might have a real hand, but it was probably just bluff. Whereas he now had a very good idea what he was going to get out of the Granger girl with his leverage. Not just whatever Transfiguration secret she'd apparently stumbled across - which had been the strong contender until now - but also the truth of what had happened today. Though no one he'd talked to was sure how badly she'd been injured...it'd be damnable luck if she didn't live long enough for him to even get started on blackmailing her.

Tracey was only half-following the conversation. She didn't have remotely the status required to participate in a discussion of this level anyway, even if she did have something to contribute, which she didn't. The girl was distracted with her own conundrum, or maybe it was just a curiosity? She'd had a disquieting feeling all day, as if she was meant to be doing something really important but she somehow couldn't quite remember what it was. Forgetfulness was not a foreign sensation to Tracey by any means - she was an indifferent student at best, and despite sharing a dorm with girls completing the same assignments, they often managed to slip her mind. It was the feeling of importance that seemed out of place.

While we are near the topic of Ms. Davis' study habits - or more properly her lack thereof - a brief digression seems in order. It is worthy of note that if she had actually opened her History of Magic textbook recently, the scrap of parchment found within - with a note scrawled in a slightly neater version of her own handwriting - would, while not exactly explaining everything, have at the least given her a bit more to go on.

Alas, she had not, and remained vaguely uneasy - bereft of any support from students outside her House due to its unsavory reputation, and unwilling to ask for assistance from within due to its uncomfortable realities.

o-o-o

"All right, I think it's settled, then? As soon as they unseal the corridor, my group will move in and try to offer Mr. Filch a hand with the clean-up. If he actually agrees, remember to use spells only when absolutely necessary, and ask permission first, otherwise do it the way he wants. If he doesn't agree, we'll try to do what we can while he's not around - he's not likely to finish in less than a day on his own. Meanwhile, Parvati will check with her sister to find out if she knows what sort of things Hermione likes that might cheer her up - it's early in the year, so we might have to do a small collection to bulk up the Benevolence Fund first if it ends up being a book we need to owl-order. Neville's got plenty of experience by now, so after dinner his team will break into smaller groups and help search for Ron's rat, while as a backup Sally-Anne's group looks into maybe finding a replacement pet for him - anonymously, if you can manage it, but coordinate for Merlin's sake, we don't want him buried in animals. Sound good to everyone?"

A chorus of smiling, enthusiastic nods and other affirmatives greeted Cedric's efficient summation, and the group of early-year Hufflepuffs set about eating.

o-o-o

"Albus," Minerva murmured, when she could no longer stand the deliberately casual dinner conversation that had occupied them since finally making it to the Great Hall, "what are you going to say?"

"You know I prefer not to plan these things too closely, Minerva," Dumbledore replied affably. "I think nothing tonight, though. It will depend somewhat on what we can glean from Miss Granger, when she - hopefully soon - regains consciousness, and Hogwarts does relish a good rumour. In any event, I'm sure something appropriate will come to mind when the moment is at hand." He smiled beatifically as he bit into a sausage. Not for the first - or, she feared, the last - time, Minerva reconsidered a great many of her life choices, and wondered if the weather in Australia was really as nice as everyone said...

On the Headmaster's opposite side, Severus Snape said nothing, which in his own opinion, was developing into a troubling trend. After this latest development, he genuinely could not tell if he was simply being stupid, being successfully manipulated, slowly going mad, or, quite possibly, all three. It had been whispered that the Dark Lord had, on rare occasions, toyed with the sanity of those who had betrayed him, rather than destroying them outright…

Further down the table, Filius Flitwick absently cut his sausages into increasingly microscopic pieces, his eyes distant. After a fair amount of shameless kibitzing, Madam Wainscott had summarily ordered everyone out of the infirmary - otherwise he'd still be there, watching over one of his newest students. He'd somehow managed to fall short as her Head of House after less than a week of classes, but he was determined to remedy that. Now that it was abundantly apparent she had latent Gryffindor tendencies, he'd just have to make a point of checking in with her more regularly, having her run any plans and insights past him so he could point out any that didn't seem entirely sane.

At the far end, Quirinus Quirrell was nearly as quiet as the Charms and Potions Professors, excepting occasional stuttered apologies as he "nervously" spilled soup or knocked over a salt cellar, but these small touches were automatic now, leaving him alone with his thoughts. It was a pity the valuable distraction afforded by the hunt for the murderer had ended so soon - he hadn't learned nearly enough about the Stone's protections to dare an attempt yet. Equally disappointing that the murderer's identity hadn't been discovered until it was too late to make any use of him without risking exposure. But this new development had suggested some interesting options…

o-o-o

A large but rather gaunt and mistreated dog, hearing someone approach the door of the cell he was unhappily occupying, hurriedly shifted his form to that of a similarly gaunt and mistreated human. He hunched and shivered slightly under the renewed oppression of the Dementors' influence on the human aspect of his psyche.

After the DMLE official, flanked by three grizzled Aurors, spoke to him, he had to ask the woman - who wore a guarded but awkward expression - to repeat herself twice. The repetition was necessary, for his weary and abused mind refused at first to accept what she was saying as something that was conceivable, let alone something that had actually happened.

It wasn't entirely a happy thought - the vengeance he'd been sustaining himself on all these years had, after all, apparently been stolen from him - but nevertheless the notion of someone else getting Peter had not once formed while he'd suffered in this place. For a moment he considered asking to be left here until Pettigrew arrived, so he could "welcome" him, but he hadn't actually gone insane. Or not quite. He laughed, but there was no mirth in it.

o-o-o

In the hospital wing, Pauline Wainscott sat at a worktable, trying to concentrate on her non-emergency duties. It had been a rather tense few minutes - at one point she had actually been forced to curtly evict the various well-meaning but not Mediwitch-trained Professors who clearly didn't really think she was entirely up to snuff, despite Dumbledore's faith in her. But in the end, she'd been able to manage the worst of her patient's shocking injuries and stabilize her for the moment. Still, she'd need rest and replenishment before her system could withstand further healing magic without risking a permanent depletion of her body's capacity for recovery. There was little enough to be done now but wait, but she kept imagining she'd heard one of the separate alarm spells she had set to watch over the girl's heart rate, blood pressure, brain activity, and general life force.

But no, there it was again - not one of her alarms, but a soft sound from the girl. She must be talking in her sleep, which was actually an encouraging sign. Pauline moved over to her bed.

"...nestly...enigmatic...rude." The girl's eyes fluttered open and she startled, half sitting up, then winced at the pain the sharp movement had no doubt produced.

"Easy, Miss Granger," the Healer said, easing her back down to the bed with gentle support on her shoulder and back. "You are safe, but you mustn't strain yourself." For a moment the girl looked relieved, but then her eyes narrowed.

"Madam Wainscott. I trust you used sufficient...ah...french toast and syrup on my wounds?" she asked, casually. Pauline cautiously revoked her own earlier sense of relief.

"Er...no…" she corrected, gently. "Some Blood-Slowing Charms, a Bone-Setter, and a Critical Restoration Spell...you'll need some more care, and a great deal of food, but you should be out of physical danger…" Now the girl's face relaxed, and she let herself sink back into the pillow.

"Good," she murmured. "Probably not dreaming. The pain was evidence, but still worth testing…" She closed her eyes, and for a moment Pauline thought she'd fallen back to sleep, but then her eyes opened again.

"Oh. Was there a rat by me, when I was found...or…"

"I don't think so, the Professors were saying something about a man who'd been hexed, but they didn't really explain, just that you'd been near or in a magical combat. You haven't shown any signs of latent curses, though if you can describe what hit you, it could help a great deal?" Again, the girl looked relieved.

"So a Full Body-Bind does block an Animagus transformation...that would've made things a lot easier, had I known...should've just asked Professor McGonagall without context," she said with a deep frown, apparently to herself. Then she seemed to realize she'd been asked a question. "Oh...spells, yes, of course you'd need to know. Let's see, a Disarming Charm, a Cruciatus Curse, a Full Body-Bind, a…well, I suppose a failed Memory Charm, then some sort of artillery spell that goes 'Bombarda Maxima' - though it didn't hit me directly - and another Disarming Charm. Oh, and a Stunning Spell and a Killing Curse hit a wall within a metre of me, but as far as I've read they don't have proximity-based side-effects, not that what I've read on the Unforgivable Curses was terribly detailed…" Pauline covered her gaping mouth with one hand as she belatedly processed everything her patient had been afflicted with - besides the Bombardment Curse that explained most of her injuries, if not how she'd survived it.

"Merlin's Beard," she gasped, and bolted to the supplies cabinet. She pulled two bottles and quickly but carefully poured a splash from each into an empty flask, swirled it, then rushed back to the girl's bed and brought it to her lips, holding it carefully so she could drink. But she turned her face to the side, avoiding the remedy.

"I can't sleep yet, if that's what-"

"It's not a sleeping draught, just a muscle relaxant, and something to promote nerve healing - both herbological, not proper potions, but you must take them as soon as possible, if I'd known a Cruciatus was involved I'd have risked waking you sooner, it never occurred to me someone might be so vile as to cast that on a child...please drink it…" The girl's eyes widened as she recognized Pauline's urgency, and she turned back, allowing the Healer to tip the liquid into her mouth. She made a face at the bitter flavour, but swallowed.

"I'm sorry," the first-year said, sounding genuinely contrite. "It's just, I have to speak to the Headmaster, that man I hexed is a fairly convincing liar, he's apparently decent at potions so he might have Veritaserum antidote, and I don't know what he's been telling them... How long was I out for?" The young woman blinked for a moment at this explanation, then glanced at her watch.

"Less than an hour. And the Headmaster asked to be notified immediately if you woke. But please, try to remain calm? Your system is very fragile right now - there are limits to how much stress the body can safely absorb, and Healing is no exception."

"I'll try. I don't think I have the energy to do otherwise, to be honest." Lines of pain in the girl's face smoothed as the concoction began to blunt the after-effects of the Cruciatus, as well as her body's other insults. Pauline withdrew her wand from its dedicated pocket in her apron.

Even when she'd finally managed to produce the spell in Defence, Professor Harbuckle had complained that she wasn't doing it properly, since she didn't use a memory, but an idea, and it wasn't even - in the Professor's opinion - a realistic idea. But it was the only thing that had ever worked for her, and it did work, so Pauline firmly imagined the world as it should be, every person free of disease, of injury, of infirmity, of pain, a world of perfect health, convinced herself - despite all evidence - that it would happen someday, and she would see it.

"Expecto Patronum!" A shining silver salamander burst from her wand, skittering across the air before her, and as usual, she couldn't help smiling at it. She hadn't tried to cast it since...since it happened, and under its soothing light, she now wished she'd been brave enough to try earlier. "Please inform Professor Dumbledore that Hermione Granger is awake and that he can talk to her...briefly." The salamander vanished in a puff of silver flame.

She'd added the trailing admonition on impulse. It was all well and good to know that in this room of the castle, even the Headmaster could not override a Healer's instructions, but she imagined it would be quite another to try to order around Albus Dumbledore to his face - he hadn't been present with the staff she'd gathered the temerity to evict earlier. But she knew Madam Pomfrey had been able to do it, somehow, even with him...she'd just have to live up to her example, should the need arise. Pauline turned back to her patient, and saw that she was propping herself up on her elbows, her eyes shining.

"While we're waiting, if you don't think it would be overly taxing for me just to watch and listen, I would like very much if you could explain the details of the spell you just cast?"

"Really, you should just be resting. I wouldn't even want you to be talking to the Headmaster if he hadn't insisted it was a matter of school safety," Pauline explained patiently. Ravenclaws, she thought.

"It's just that," the girl persisted, "a spell to send messages seems like something everyone should be taught. And it...felt?...like it was a broad variant of a Cheering Charm, which would make it even more useful in, you know, dire situations…"

Oh, so that was the problem.

"I know you've had a bad turn, and I can't imagine how frightening all this must've been for you, but really, you're safe now. Hogwarts is really very safe as a rule, nothing like this has happened in ages. It's best to trust the Professors to handle such things and just concentrate on your studies."

"Learning magic is part of my studies," the girl pointed out. "And while I'm sure you're right - I know logically it's wrong to extrapolate the rest of my time at Hogwarts based on one unlikely event - but emotionally I'd feel much better if I knew a way to directly call for help if, say, someone was trying to kill me. Again." Even in her apparent vehemence the first-year looked a bit uncertain, as if doubting the quality of her own argument, and Pauline soldiered on.

"I couldn't possibly...even if we skipped over it being a fifth-year spell, it took me ages to learn and I don't do it entirely right, and I'm not a Professor," insisted Madam Wainscott. "When you're well, you can ask Professor Quirrell. Now I must ask that you lie back and rest, you can't afford to get agitated right now."

"I'm not agitated, I'm just-" the girl paused and took a breath. "All right, maybe I was a bit agitated." She lowered herself to the pillow again, then frowned. "Wait. It's a Defence spell? I mean, Defence class is already a bit haphazard about what it includes, and effective communication is a good form of defence, but…"

"Well, yes. But sending messages with it is actually something the Headmaster showed me how to do when I came on here. Properly, it's only meant as a defence against Lethifolds and Dementors." Pauline shuddered, and the girl's frown deepened.

"I've seen a reference to Lethifolds, and from context I inferred they were pretty nasty. But I thought Dementors were the guards at Azkaban, that it was a profession, like Auror, or Unspeakable?"

"Oh heavens no," breathed Pauline. "That is, yes, they're tasked with guarding Azkaban, but they're about the Darkest creature we know of, including actual Dark wizards." Her patient lapsed into thoughtfulness. "Anyway, I should let you rest until the Headmaster-"

"What exactly do Dementors do...that makes such a Dark creature appropriate prison guards?" the girl interrupted, in a very quiet voice. Pauline remembered that the girl was muggleborn - she was probably quite wrongly but understandably worried about the man who'd cursed her, that he might somehow escape. Ordinarily describing such a thing to a young child wasn't something she'd even consider, let alone one who was already recovering from an ordeal. But in this unique case, if it might comfort her to know how perfect a prison Azkaban was…

She explained what Dementors were.

o-o-o

After Madam Wainscott's Patronus appeared at his shoulder and delivered its message, Albus excused himself from the Head Table and quickly made his way towards the hospital wing.

The dreadful tale that Mr. Pettigrew had told, under the influence of Veritaserum, was fantastical to say the least. That he could have been so misjudged by everyone, and so successfully framed Sirius Black for the Potters' betrayal seemed as shocking and unlikely as Sirius' apparent betrayal had been in the first place. But not quite. Not enough that - unlike then - he wouldn't thoroughly verify the facts of the matter. His account of the murder of Poppy Pomfrey did seem to match what little they knew, though. Pettigrew was already in the hands of the DMLE, Alastor had taken him personally, and was going to watch him unblinkingly - a half-literal expression, in the grizzled Auror's case - for a full day to ensure any hypothetical Veritaserum Antidote would have become ineffective, then dose him and question him again.

Alastor had immediately raised the possibility that the confession was false and part of some deeper plot to get Sirius Black released from Azkaban...there was nothing to say they couldn't both have been traitors, and one turned on the other when Voldemort fell, or that Voldemort was playing some very long game with the once-friends. But against the mere possibility an innocent man had spent a decade in Azkaban, Albus had lobbied heavily for Black to be taken into temporary protective custody outside the prison as a possible witness. Guarded at all times by a minimum of three veteran Aurors, of course, just in case. Nevertheless, Albus had already begun to marinate in a new mix of guilt and regret. Things had been so hectic right after Tom's 'miscalculation'...in some ways worse, as Death Eaters lashed out without leadership or aim. He'd known that Bartemius was cutting corners, sometimes forgoing trials altogether. And on some level, he hadn't wanted to hear Sirius explain why he'd betrayed their cause, his best friend, and his own godson. He'd never understood the lust for power, for dominance, that other Death Eaters had espoused, and to hear it from the lips of someone he'd trusted - again - wasn't something he was eager to experience.

But mostly, he'd simply been busy.

Just as now, when he'd been so busy with his delicate plans to try to contain Voldemort - to end Tom's sad story with the minimum of suffering to all involved - that he'd miscalculated, presumed Poppy's death was Riddle showing his hand, and moved to trap him in the castle with the eleven-year-old boy who was apparently the sole being with any hope of destroying him. Even while knowing that the Prophecy constrained Time but did not choose which of them would fall to the other. But despite his careful scrutiny, an Animagus transformation had been sufficient to evade his notice, and another student had nearly died because of his own blindness.

Still, if Peter's confessions were accurate, they would shortly have Tom's wand, and would have deprived him of his strongest tool and most secret ally in a single stroke. A stroke delivered not by himself, or Severus, or even a certain first-year Gryffindor, but rather a first-year Ravenclaw muggleborn. To say it was unexpected was putting it mildly. And yet...

Severus had, only yesterday, asked him if he knew anything of note about Hermione Granger. Which, aside from Minerva giving her closer Transfiguration supervision, he had not. But the Potions Master had said nothing further, which suggested he was suspicious about something but had not yet become certain enough to say. He had asked similar questions about a few other students and half the staff besides. As loyal as he judged Severus now to be, he was Slytherin to his bones, and the man would not risk tarnishing his self-image by sharing unfounded supposition that might turn out to be baseless. Of course beyond that, on a much deeper level, he had once been taught a harsh lesson indeed about sharing incomplete information.

When their prisoner had given his unwilling account of his encounter with Miss Granger, Alastor had predictably noted certain inconsistencies in the story, the failed Memory Charm, the weak Body-Bind - though the rest was plausible, if barely, as the actions of a particularly precocious first-year - and suggested immediately performing an impractical number of strenuous examinations of the girl that might've been life-threatening even if she wasn't recovering from serious injuries. Under normal circumstances, Severus ought to have made some dryly cutting remarks - his natural skepticism and scorn was an excellent check to Alastor's increasingly rampant paranoia - but he had again, said nothing. Perhaps it was worth pressing him on the matter, but he'd decide after speaking to the girl and forming his own opinions - and he had forbid any interrogations until after that point.

The old wizard paused a few spans from the hospital wing doors as he came upon a third-year Ravenclaw loitering in the corridor.

"Mr. Davies," he greeted him, curiously.

"Professor," returned the boy, in a respectful but cautious tone.

"I understand that Madam Wainscott has cleared the hospital wing, but if you have an actual medical need, you needn't wait outside…"

"Oh, no, sir. I just wanted to be here for Hermione, if she...I mean...I feel a little responsible." Albus raised an eyebrow, and the boy wilted a bit. "I...after Madam Pomfrey, I was just sure she wouldn't make a mistake like that, and some of the lower-years talked about alternative explanations. She just took it very seriously, she was really investigating, and I encouraged her. Is it true, Madam Pomfrey was murdered, and Hermione caught him?"

"What truly happened is still a matter of some debate, though I commend you - your loyalty and faith in Madam Pomfrey's professionalism is well-founded. As for your responsibility in the matter...did you know your Housemate was planning to confront a suspected murderer herself?" The boy shook his head.

"Merlin, no, I'd have told her to go to Professor Flitwick or yourself straight away." Albus nodded.

"And are you taking Divination this year?" Davies blinked at the non-sequitur, then again shook his head.

"No, sir. Arithmancy, Ancient Runes and Care of Magical Creatures."

"Well. If you had somehow been capable of reliably predicting today's events in advance, I dare say I would be justified in making you a co-Professor along with Professor Trelawney. As it is, I think you deserve no blame." The boy nodded, though he seemed unsatisfied with this absolution. "You still have a few minutes to get some dinner. I will ask Madam Wainscott to see that you are informed when Miss Granger is fit to receive visitors."

"Thank you, Headmaster," he said after a moment's hesitation, then headed off at a brisk walk. Albus had nearly reached the hospital wing entrance when he was brought up short again.

"-serious?!" The high-pitched shout had been audible even through the closed doors to the hospital wing. Raising an eyebrow, he entered and quietly closed the door behind him, adding a Sound-proofing Spell to them with a gesture. For the moment, he was unnoticed by the other occupants of the room.

The only patient was a small girl, struggling to support her sitting position with one hand as the other was occupied in violently shaking a finger at Madam Wainscott. The girl's face was red and her untamed brown hair danced in a mad cloud around her head, while the Healer frantically tried to calm her patient. A two-chime pattern was insistently repeating above the girl's bed, but it was largely drowned out by her continued shouting.

"Do you even realize how insane that is? There are dozens of laws, hundreds, that carry mandatory sentences in Azkaban, a lot not even for violent crimes - not that that would be an excuse anyway! For short sentences, you're just making them worse people when they get out than when they went in! For long ones, it's basically execution by extended torture. And then if that somehow isn't bad enough, if someone justifiably escapes, you can whistle up one of these things to EAT their SOUL - whatever that actually means?! Here I'd thought normal prisons were shamefully mismanaged, but apparently magic is better at everything, and you've managed to leapfrog them straight to concentration camps guarded by literal demons!"

"Please, Miss Granger, you must calm down, you'll do yourself permanent harm," begged Madam Wainscott, trying with only partial success to press the girl back down to the bed.

"Calm down?" Her expression was disbelieving. "The Ministry is evil. Wizards are evil. You can't just give people to things like that and not be evil, no matter what they've done, no matter how you rationalize it."

"You are not entirely wrong, Miss Granger," Albus said, mildly. The room fell silent as the remark settled heavily over everyone present. For her part, the Healer looked both aghast and relieved. The girl, meanwhile, was undergoing what he'd come to think of as Standard Reaction Number Two to meeting him in person for the first time, which involved a fair amount of stammering and avoiding eye contact. To her credit, her indignation was rapidly spurring her past that stage, though she seemed somewhat at a loss as to how to continue, opening and closing her mouth without managing to produce any words. "Pauline?" he asked, turning to the Healer.

"I-I'm sorry Headmaster, she asked about Dementors and I thought it would help, knowing how secure Azkaban was, that her attacker would never escape…" The girl on the bed made a brief choking noise.

"It would seem not, though it was an understandable notion under the circumstances. I presume by your resort to, ah, physical persuasion that employing additional spells or potions upon Miss Granger is contraindicated?" The girl had let herself fall back into the bed, but the Healer's hand was still on her shoulder - she hastily withdrew it while nodding emphatically.

"Yes, Headmaster, emergency use only...though she was nearly to the point that a Slumber Charm would've been worth the risk," she confirmed, casting a stern glance at her patient. It was lost upon the girl, however, who had closed her eyes and seemed to be deliberately taking a series of deep breaths, which had in turn quieted the monitoring charms.

"I will make an effort not to tire Miss Granger needlessly, but I do need to speak with her. Privately, I'm afraid." At the Healer's conflicted expression, he raised a palm in a conciliatory gesture. "I don't intend to move her, nor to ask you to leave your patient...I will use an ambient privacy charm, but make specific exclusions for your monitoring spells. Is that acceptable?" Pauline nodded.

"I suppose. But please, Headmaster, sir - I've given her what aid I can for the moment, but the assaults upon her included a Cruciatus Curse among other things - do try to make it short and avoid upsetting her...further...?" Albus' eyebrows rose, but he nodded. The young woman moved to a worktable and made a pretense of useful labor while she kept the bed constantly in her peripheral vision. Albus moved to the girl's bed and sat upon a stool beside it, conjured with a lazy wave of his hand.

He withdrew a wand of terrible power - the wizard made it a rule to remind himself of that every time he touched it - and turned it gently in a horizontal circle. The quiet sounds of the room around the bed faded away, and the room itself was obscured by a grey haze, until they seemed to be resting inside an opaque and sound-proof egg, which they were.

By this time the girl had finished her deep-breathing exercises and opened her eyes, though after a quick glance around, she seemed to be considering resuming them.

"You have nothing to fear from me, Miss Granger," he noted.

"I'm sorry, Headmaster. It's just...I'm having some anxiety-management issues, here." Her eyes seemed to be more calm, though still betraying a tumult of emotions beneath.

"I quite understand, Miss Granger. And please, the honorific is not necessary - Professor is sufficient, and preferred, if referring to me so would not cause you discomfort." She gave him a queer look.

"Alright. Professor. I...ugh. False urgency, right. Putting aside Azkaban, for the moment. The man who was found paralyzed near me - assuming he was a short, stocky, pointy-nosed, rat Animagus - admitted to me that he murdered Madam Pomfrey and made it look like an accident. I don't know what he's been telling you, but-" Albus raised a palm.

"The individual in question, one Peter Pettigrew, is indeed in custody, and has under Veritaserum divulged the details of that despicable act...among others. Your efforts in exposing him, while perhaps ill-advised, are much appreciated. Though there do remain a considerable number of questions about the affair…if you would care to relate events from your perspective, I hope it will clear matters up significantly?" The girl, who had visibly relaxed when he'd confirmed Pettigrew's status, now tensed and broke eye contact, rather too quickly for it to be simple reticence or shyness. Interesting.

"I'm sorry I didn't take it up with a Professor, sir. I know what I did was reckless and stupid. I did ask Professor Quirrell for hypothetical tactical advice, and I actually tried to talk to you about it at one point, but I didn't know how to get into your office, and then I talked myself out of it. It was just...the 'Seer's Hex' thing...I was sure no one would believe me without actual evidence - or worse, send me to St. Mungo's - and I didn't have any until I confronted him." Albus nodded.

"For future reference, any Professor can arrange a meeting with me, with sufficient reason, though typically students would do so through their Head of House. But in the interests of avoiding any similar missed opportunities for collaboration, the password to my office this year is 'chocolate frog'. I trust that you will keep this to yourself, and not abuse the privilege?" He gave her an amused smile as she nodded mutely. "As for your concerns about staff giving credence to your suspicions...I agree, it was an unfortunate situation. But I would urge you to make every effort to give us the benefit of the doubt, in the future?" The Ravenclaw looked conflicted.

"I...I would like to, Professor, but...you knew, didn't you? That it was murder? And you sealed him in with us. And then there's Azkaban, and house elves, for that matter. I'd been assuming everything in magical Britain was pretty much the same, deep down, only plus magic, but now it seems like there are some pretty serious ethical differences. And you admitted it was evil. I'm…" she swallowed heavily. Albus carefully considered his words.

"Wizards are not angels, Miss Granger, any more than muggles are. There is the capacity for great evil in us, as well as great good, and among any sufficiently large number of people you will find examples of both, with most falling somewhere between. I will note that things are not always as they appear, though in the case of Azkaban, I cannot truly claim otherwise. But do not mistake the presence of evil for surrender to it. Many people, myself included, actively oppose the Ministry's use of Dementors, but we do not yet outnumber the influence of those who support it. Regrettably, the average wizard is more concerned with what happens to those he feels to be like himself than...convicted criminals hundreds of miles away, who in his mind, knew what they risked when they broke the law. Can you truly say things are different among muggles?"

"I think the United Kingdom outlawed capital punishment twenty years ago, and we haven't tortured people for rather longer than that," the girl noted, pointedly. Albus nodded.

"And so we are quite behind the times, shamefully in this case. Perhaps you are right, that as a whole, wizards might make decisions that - given your upbringing - you would not expect, or support. But with rare exception, individually, Hogwarts' Professors are intelligent people of high character. If you perceive an injustice, or a wrong - and share it - we will give your concerns a fair hearing." The young girl's frown did not lighten, but she nodded.

"And locking a murderer in a boarding school with a bunch of children?" she asked. Albus had been hoping in his initial concession that she would not have noticed he hadn't addressed that part.

"Though I believe I had good reasons to act as I did, at this point I am regrettably not at liberty to explain them fully to you without ostensibly putting a great many people in even worse jeopardy. I will say that the protections for Hogwarts students are quite numerous, and many are exceedingly subtle - it was not as great a risk as you might imagine. But nevertheless, there was danger, and I deeply regret both the necessity, and the suffering it brought you."

"That's...I appreciate that, or I'm trying to, but that's...really not good enough?" The girl was trying to maintain a stern front, but the rise in her voice's pitch betrayed her uncertainty.

"Miss Granger, I fear you are experiencing a severe instance of what I believe muggles call 'culture shock'. The flexibility and power of magic supports a society in which certain levels of risk, that muggles might reasonably consider completely unacceptable, are simply everyday encounters. As I have said, it is not perfect by any means. But it is true to itself. Your impulse may be to withdraw from it, to give up your studies and live as a muggle. Or depending on what your parents learn of these events, they may attempt to withdraw you and prohibit you from returning. It has happened before. But magical Britain needs more people such as yourself, who can look at a criminal, or a house elf, and still see a feeling being, worthy of basic decency. People who can drag us by our broomsticks towards the fast-approaching third millennium. People who, even when they feel there is no authority they may turn to, will still try to do what is right, even at great personal risk." He could see from her face that she wasn't comfortable either with the implied compliments or the parallel he'd drawn.

"I just wanted to go to school," she said, after a moment. "It's all I've ever wanted. The past few years, I almost always had already read what the teachers were teaching, but there were still always things I could learn, and I can't help reading ahead, so I can understand. And magic...it's a whole new world, literally. But all these...important things...I just...I don't know if I can handle it." The Headmaster smiled kindly and patted her hand.

"An obvious mark of quality is rising to the occasion, when necessary. But there is no rush, young lady! You likely have a full century of life ahead of you, at least, and while you show great promise, you do not yet bear responsibility for the world's troubles. Ample time to learn, and later, when you've gained wisdom to match your knowledge, to act." This little bit of inspiration didn't seem to land well, as the girl's expression took on a sickly cast, and it seemed like she might begin to cry. But before he could begin to correct the matter, she shook her head sharply, then met his gaze evenly.

"I...have to tell you some things. Not just the murderer, but a lot more than that. I don't know if it's the right thing to do, but I can't say nothing." She hesitated and her eyes took on a haunted cast that no young child's should, but that he'd nevertheless seen more times than he cared to remember.

"'Help will always be given at Hogwarts, to those who ask for it'," he noted gently, quoting one of the Founders. The girl nodded.

"I hope so. There...might not be as much time as you think. But it would be silly not to at least ask first." She paused, gathering her thoughts. "Suppose I - believed - that Time had been changed, somehow, and I was...will be?...partially responsible. Would it be safe...or advisable, for me to tell you the details? If it lends any credence, I'm clear of the Conditional Obscuration on the relevant laws." Albus' eyebrows climbed skyward.

"Given that preface...I think you must, Miss Granger. If I decide it is knowledge I Ought Not to Know, I'm confident I can restore my own ignorance, and yours - if necessary, and if you consented, of course." The first-year stared at him for a moment, several emotions dueling for dominance on her face, though surprise was only faintly represented.

"I suppose if any Obliviation is ethically acceptable, a self-imposed one would qualify. But honestly, wizards seem far more free with that than they really ought to be." She shook her head and took a deep breath. "All right. I suppose it all started - in objective chronology if not my own episodic sort - during my first trip to Diagon Alley, with a book..."

o-o-o-o-o

A/N: I live! Apologies for the epic-length posting hiatus, you know how these things are. I do have one short chapter ready after this one, and then we'll see if I can get back on a regular posting schedule, but no guarantees other than yes, I will continue the story to its natural end, however long that takes.

Thanks to /u/HermioneGPEV for pointing out a confusing offset qualifier in Ch. 18!